<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Looking-glasse for, or an awakening word to the superiour and inferiour officers, with all others, belonging to the Armies of England, Scotland, and Ireland; more especially to those, who have the least spark of grace or principles of true honesty remaining in them. Wherein is set before them, and presented to the world, some passages contained in severall of their declarations, remonstrances, and engagements, &amp;c. speciously pretending for the just rights and liberties of the people, in the way of a common wealth, opposed to monarchy; and more especially, for the advancement of the kingdome of Christ, and his Saints ruling for him till he comes himself. With some marginall annotations, whereby (in some measure) is manifested how evidently they are declined and turned aside from the principles of justice and righteousness, therein contained. As also how they justifie the proceedings of those, who (in the prosecution of these principles of justice and righteousnesse,) shall oppose their back-slidings.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88526</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862937</idno>
  <idno type="VID">115117</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240941718</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3023</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E891_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202753</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862937</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99862937e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88526)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115117)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 134:E891[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Looking-glasse for, or an awakening word to the superiour and inferiour officers, with all others, belonging to the Armies of England, Scotland, and Ireland; more especially to those, who have the least spark of grace or principles of true honesty remaining in them. Wherein is set before them, and presented to the world, some passages contained in severall of their declarations, remonstrances, and engagements, &amp;c. speciously pretending for the just rights and liberties of the people, in the way of a common wealth, opposed to monarchy; and more especially, for the advancement of the kingdome of Christ, and his Saints ruling for him till he comes himself. With some marginall annotations, whereby (in some measure) is manifested how evidently they are declined and turned aside from the principles of justice and righteousness, therein contained. As also how they justifie the proceedings of those, who (in the prosecution of these principles of justice and righteousnesse,) shall oppose their back-slidings.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 22 1656".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115117:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Looking Glasse FOR,</hi> Or An <hi>AWAKENING WORD</hi> TO The Superiour and Inferiour Officers, with all others, belonging to the Armies of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> more especially to those, who have the least Spark of grace or Principles of true honesty remaining in them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein is set before them, and presented to the World, some Passages contained in severall of their Declarations, Remonstrances, and Engagements,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Speciously pretending for the just Rights and Liberties of the People, in the way of a Common wealth, opposed to Monarchy; and more especially, for the Advancement of the Kingdome of Christ, and his Saints ruling for him till he comes himself.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With some Marginall Annotations, whereby (in some measure) is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested how evidently they are declined and turned aside from the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Justice and Righteousness, therein contained.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As also how they justifie the proceedings of those, who (in the prosecution of these principles of Justice and Righteousnesse,) shall oppose their back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slidings.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Gall. 2.18.</hi>
                  </bibl> For if I build again the things which I destroyed, I make my self a transgressor.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 2.3.</hi>
                  </bibl> And thinkest thou this O man, that judgest them that do such things, and doest the same; that thou shalt escape the judgment of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Jer. 2.14.</hi>
                  </bibl> Is Israel a servant? is he a home born slave? Why is he spoiled?</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>V. 19.</hi>
                  </bibl> Thine own wickednesse shall correct thee, and thy backsliding shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thee; Know therefore and see, that is is an evill thing and bitter, that thou hast forsaken the Lord thy God, and that my fear is not in thee saith the Lord God of hosts.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_army">
            <pb facs="tcp:115117:2"/>
            <head>To the Army.</head>
            <p>HAving perused many of your Declarations, Remonstrances, and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> made before the Lord and to the People in the day of our st aights, to engage him, and them unto you, and observing in your expressions therein, such specious pretences to justice and righteousnesse, and the preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Peoples Rights and Liberties, in opposition to all Tiranny and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression whatsoever; and this in the way of a Common-wealth, or Free-state, opposed to a Monarch, or single person. As also for the advancement of the Kingdome of Jesus Chri t, and that you would endeavour to put the Power of this Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto the hands of his Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll he comes himself. Considering also the eminent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>resence o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lord, the Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, Prayers, Appeals, and love of his people engaged with you, and your dread &amp; terrour upon the enemy at home and the Nations abroad, whilest you were acted by these honest principles. I cannot but very much wonder that you should so soon forsake the Lord, and be s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ating your selves upon that foundation, and doing those very things, you so much condemned in others; and were so instrumentall to destroy. Surely that presence of the Lord, and the love of his faithfull people, as emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently withdrawing from you, since you first forsook him, and turned aside in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to these by and crooked paths; declares plainly (and it cannot but leave this dint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ehinde it upon your sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rits, that your present way and practise is not good; and therefore its bests for you before it be too late (according to <hi>2 Hos. 2.</hi>) to return unto your first husband, and walk in that good old way, wherein he shined upon you, for you cannot but acknowledge that it was better with you then, than now?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>I hope the subject matter of this Book needs not many words to invite thee to a se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ious view thereof, but rather expect thou art waiting for it, than now come to be questioning of it: surely it is not my delight to be raking into other mens sores, but the danger of the whole body forceth me to this Corosive, least through too much tendernesse it perish; besides, the necessity which lyeth upon all men in this juncture of time, to appear for Christ, and the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Freedome; and therefore thou art desired, na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rowly to peruse it, and in thy place, to be speaking, and doing, what thou canst for the truth in this day least thou come under the repr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>of of the Prophet, Isa. <hi>59.4. None calleth, for Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ice, nor any man pleads for truth,</hi> &amp;c. And let nor the feare o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man discourage thee, or the consideration of worldly relations, and engagements hinder thee, but up and be adoing, and the Lord be with thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115117:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>Looking-Glasse</hi> or an <hi>Awakening Word</hi> to the Superiour, and Inferiour Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, with all others belonging to the Armies of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> more especially to those, who have the least spark of grace, or principle of true honesty remaining in them.</head>
            <div type="text">
               <head>In a Declaration or Representation of the Army, tendered to the Parliament, <hi>June</hi> 14. 1647. </head>
               <p>Page <hi>4.</hi> (say they.)</p>
               <p>VVE are not a meer Merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Army, hired to serve an Arbitrary power of State, but called forth and conjured by the several Declarations of Parliament to the Defence of the Peoples just Rights and Liberties. And so we took up arms in judgment and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science to those ends, and have so continued them, and are resolved according to your first just desiree in your Declarations, and such principles, as we have received from your frequent informations, and our own common sense concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing those our fundamental Rights and Liberties; to assert and vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the just Power and Rights of this Nation in Parliament, for those common, ends premised a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all Arbitrary Power, Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Oppression, and against all particular parties, or interests whatsoever, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115117:3"/>
               <p>And truly such kingdomes as have according both to the law of nature, &amp; Nations appeard to the vindication of their just rights, and liberties, have proceeded much higher, as our bretheren of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land who in the first begining, of these late differences associated in Covenant from the very same grounds and principles, having no visible for me either of Parliament o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> King to countinance them, and as they were therein justified, and protected, by their own, and this kingdome also, so we justly shall expect to be, we need not mention the state of the Netherland, the Portugalls, and others all proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the same principles, of Right and Freedome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Parlament hath declared it no resisting of Magistracy to side with just Principles and Law of Nature and Nations, being that law upon which we have assisted you, and that the soldiery may lawfully hold the hands of the Generall who will turne his canon against his Army: The Seamen the hands of that Pilot who willfully rune the ship upon a Rock (as our bretheren of Scotland argued) and such were the proceedings of our Ancestors of famous memory to the purchasing of such rights and liberties as they have enjoyed through the price of their bloud
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115117:3"/> and we both by that and the latter bloud of our deare freinds, and fell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ow souldiers, with the hazard of our own, do now lay claime too.</p>
               <p>Nor is that supreme end the glory of God wanting in these ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to set a price upon all such pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of righteousnes and Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, it being one witnes of God in the world to cary on a Testimony against the injustice, and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes of men, and against the miscariage of Governments when corrupted or declining from their Origional, and Primitive glory. These things we mention but to compare proceedings and to shew that we are so much the more Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable, and warranted in what we do, by how much we come short of that height, and measure of proceedings which the people in free Kingdoms, and Nations have formerly practised, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are so far from designing, or complying to have an absolute, or Arbitary power fixed, or settled for continuance in any persons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, as that if we might be sure to obtaine it, we cannot wish to have it so in the persons of any whom we could most confide in, or who should appeare most of our owne opinions and principles, or whom we might have most assur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of or intrest in, but we doe and shall much rather wish, that the authority of this Kingdome in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament rightly constituted may ever stand and have its course, &amp;c. which may give most hopes of justice, and Righteousnesse, to flow down equally to all, in that its an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Chonnell, without any O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertures
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115117:4"/> tending either to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>through that foundation of Order and government in this Kingdom, or to ingrosse that power for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity into the hands of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular persons or party whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And do also declare as to Parliaments.</p>
               <p>That those who appeare most Righteous, and for common good having an unlimited power fixed in them dureing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife or pleasure in time may be corrupt, and settle into parties, or factions, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the only way to provide for this is, that however unjust, or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the persons of Parliament men in present or future may prove or whatever ill they may doe to particular parties (or to the whole in particular things) during their respective termes, or periods, yet they shall not have the temptation or advantage of an unlimited pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er fixed in them during their own pleasures, whereby to perpetuate injustice, and oppression upon any (without end and remedy) or to Advance and uphold, one particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar party, Faction or intrests, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, to the oppression, or previ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the community, and the enslaving the Kingdom to all poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but that the people may have an equal hope, or possibility, if they have made an ill choice at one time to mend it in another, and the members of the house themselves may be in acapacity to tast of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115117:4"/> as well as Rule, and may so be enclined, to consider of other mens cases, as what may come to be their own.</p>
               <p>And doe declare that the Legislative power and the power of finall judgements, most unfit and dangerous (as to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Intrest) to be fixd in the persons of any dureing life, or at their own pleasures, and wher ever it is, and continues so it renders that state noe better then a Tyran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y or the people subjected to it no better then vassal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>IF the opposing Arbitrary power, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and oppression exercised by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular parties or intere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts, &amp; the asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the peoples just power and rights in their Representors, assembled in the Supream authority, was that by which you would declare you were not a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary Army hired to serve the arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry power of a state. How then can your selves or others, who with soberness weigh things, judge otherwise of you, who not onely ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, but with Swords by your sides uphold your Generall, who by deceit and violence hath rooted up these very foundations of Right and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; advancing himself and interest upon their ruines. And if it were sound doctrine in that day for you to stand up, and plead against such Tyrany and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, if exercised by them, who were a lawfull power; will it not then justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie those who have not Apostatized from but are more refined in those honest prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that shall plead and rise up against the very same, and greater Oppression exercised by your Protector and his Councel, who are an unlawfull and usurping Power.</p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115117:3"/>
                  <p>And if you might in that day honest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Vindicate and justifie your practise by the examples of the free people of other Nations, and plead the rationality and justnes of the Scots associating in Covenant for the redemption of their Liberties, entrench upon by their King without any visible forme of Authority to owne them therein, then for shame condemne your selves for what you have said already, be silent and open your mouthes no more for the fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ure, against those who upon more refined principles having the glory of God, and good of the Nation singly in their eye, that are and shall be raised up by him, to stand up and plead for in Order thereto a perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of things according to the true intent of all those glorious words, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynd in your severall Declarations Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrances and Engagements though they have no forme of an Authority to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance or owne them for if it were lawfull then it is so now.</p>
                  <p>And if in the Parlaments Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and yours it were no resisting of Magistracy then to side with just princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and that according to the Law of nature and Nations, the most Lawfull Authority might be opposed if intrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Nations rights and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and doe plead the justnes of it from the practise of our Ancestors and the successe they had therein. Then by your own words they are excused from resisting of magistracy, who in this day are siding with, and pleading for the very same asserted Kights and freedoms now entrench upon by your Protector, who is no magistrate, but an usurper.</p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115117:3"/>
                  <p>And douptles such may expect noe lesse a blessing from God in beareing their witnes against the justice, and unrighteousnes of them in power who have so far declined their former honest principles declared in their remonstran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Declarations and Engagements, &amp;c. As thay have builded again, and do stand upon the very foundation, they had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed with so large, an expence of bloud, and treasure, and their practise therein is justified (if you should blame them) not only by the people of other Nation, but by yours also.</p>
                  <p>By these words it appeares that some in that day feared that you would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose such persons to rule over them as would cheifly be for the advance of your particular Intrest, and the sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing whatever closed not with it, and to clear your selves from this, you decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that to do so were to entrench upon the peoples rights, &amp;c. And that the only way to bring in equal righteousnes &amp; ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, to all without respect to persons, &amp; to keep out vassels to particular and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intrests, was that men who had not forfeited that Liberty might chuse their Rulers. But do you not after all these specious pretences to reason and justice, stand by and uphold a few of your own society, with others, who contrary to law and the consent of the people, have fixed this power, and way of Government
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115117:4"/> in the hands of your Generall and a Councell, (who are vassalls to his intrest) during life, to the inflaving of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who comply not with his and your private Intres<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, whereby that which they then feared is come upon them.</p>
                  <p>And if to put the government du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring life or pleasure into the hands of such persons as appeare most righteous and for common good may so endanger their being corrupt and settling into perties, as without dispute would end, in the support of their own intrests to the oppressing of others, and the onely way to hinder the perpetuating this slavery and oppression be that this power should be limited by certain periods put to their sitting and others to be chosen in their stead, which doubtlesse according to the honest spirit which acted then and the same spirit more refined, which is brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing now and right reason, is the only way to hinder ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, slavery and bond age from comming upon the Nation then what bondage and slavery have you (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all these glorious words and profession brought upon the Saints and people of the Nation, either in your setting up or maintaining, now he is up a single person and his Councell with an unlimited pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er during life, with provision for a con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inuance thereof in these that shall succeed him, whereby (except the Lord prevent) we are irrecoverably brought under a perpetuall tyrany vassallage, and oppression againe which your selves confesse in the following words.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <head>In a Representation of the desires of the Officers and Souldiers of a Regiment of horse quarterd in the County of Northumberland to the Lord Generall Fairefax.</head>
               <p>They hold forth the first ground, and the of tyrany over the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ree borne people of this Nation to proceed from the Bastard of <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> the sixth Duke of Normandy, who to prevent the English of all recovery and relief by their parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in future, he created Lords by his Patent, and Prerogative, to si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by succession in Parliament, as Representors of his conquest and Tyrany over us, and not by Election of the People, as the Representors and Patrons of the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>And to add unto this, to make his U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pation firme and inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he subdued the Law-giving Power of the free people of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land in their Parliaments, to the Negative voice of himself and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And under the yoak of this Norman captivity and villai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, we have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eld by that succession, even to this day.</p>
               <p>And this King, to uphold the constitution and settlement of those principles, and forms of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and in them his dominion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115117:5"/> over us, brought a cruel and blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy war upon this Nation, against whom with your Excellency, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der authority of Parliament, we have freely engaged; to the end we might rescue the legislative Powers of our English Parliament, our free Customes, and native Rights, from the bondage of that Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and so free our selves, and all the people, from the common Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions of the Land, by a settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a just and equall government of Right, and Freedome.</p>
               <p>But instead of this, we finde the Parliament betake themselves to a complyance and Treaty, with our Conquered Enemy, courting his pleasure, and allowing him a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative voice, in the passing all Acts of Parliament: Whereby our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnity, our Laws, and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are all subjected to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession, his will, advanced above all laws, above the Parliament and people, and himself put out of the reach of Justice, and made accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to none; unto which yoak of Norman Captivity (after all the bloud that hath been spilt against it) We are loath to be subjected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as we see both we and all the people must needs be, except the Army interpose betwixt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and their destroyers, and make good their Engagement at New-market Heath, with all their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrances, Declarations, and Promises to the people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Upon which, they call upon the Generall, to put forth his power, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115117:5"/> and release of this oppressed Nation; in order to which, they present their desires under 38. particular heads: But for brevitie sake, there are onely four of them mentioned in this place, <hi>viz.</hi> 2. 20. 22. 28. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That the exaction of Tythes and all manner of Impropriations be removed; and that the publick Ministry be otherwise provided for.</p>
               <p n="20">20. That our Parliament for the future be secured, and cleared from the Negative voice of any single person, or persons whatsoever.</p>
               <p n="22">22. That a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l Statutes, Laws, and Acts of Parliament, be made and run onely in the name of the Commons of England assembled in Parliament.</p>
               <p n="28">28. That no man be kept in Prison above a moneth, but in that space to be brought to a Tryall by a lawfull Jury of his equals, or else to be discharged of course.</p>
               <p>For these things we declare, and with our swords in our hands, as we are Souldiers, we challenge them as the price and purchase of our bloud, to live and dye for them, against all Opposers what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115117:6"/> And as we are English men we claim them as our own inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and birth-right; and do beg the Generall to give them as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance and encouragement, for the accomplishment of these things, that themselves, the people and Generations to come, may have just cause to blesse God for his righteous conduct, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</head>
                  <p>And will it not be the same if your Protector by his power and force bring in his Bashaws, or Maj. Generals, chosen neither by God nor his people, to sit as Lords for the support of his Inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st, and that over a Parliament (so called) not of the peoples, but his own chusing, is not this greater tyranny then that so much complained of, which the Basturd exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised in that day.</p>
                  <p>And hath not your Protector done the same, for by his negative voice, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his power in the Militia, he will let no law passe though never so much for Publique welfare if it entrench upon his Ʋsurpation, and if the peoples Represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors do not gratify his lusts therein he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently dissolves them, wherefore are we not under the Norman Yoak now as we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l as formerly?</p>
                  <p>And doth not your Protectors saying, he will lay down his old bones in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining his usurpt Power, declare, that another blouldy war will unavoyda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115117:5"/> come upon the Nation? For can it be imagined, that after the expense of of much bloud and treasure, also the faith, prayers, and appeales of the Saints put up, and your Declarations, Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strances and Engagements, for our just Rights and Freedomes, and against these principles and formes of Tyranny, that the Lord will suffer us to be of so base and low a spirit, as to bow our Necks to the very same Yoaks of Tyrany again.</p>
                  <p>And have not some persons in the Army and elsewhere, who being adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated from their virgin spirit and principles, and looking at the favour and fear of man more than at the Lord, who have lately complyed with your Protectors interest, to the hatching and bringing forth a Paper, called the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument of Government: Whereby is given him a Negative voice, so much opposed and denyed to the late King. Whereby our persons, laws, libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies, and the supreme Authority of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are subjected to his lust, and he exempted from the reach of Justice, and being so, why may we not complain, and declare against these things, and be as unwilling to submit thereto, as you to the very same in the King: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>case you uphold him in the violation of all these wholesome words, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, as justly endeavour to free our selves and Countrey from our present Oppression, as you might have done in that day.</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115117:5"/>
                  <p>Contrary to this not onely Tythes, but the law to compel those to pay treble damages, who refused to pay them is esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished also notwithstanding your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector said to Mr. <hi>Jessy</hi> and others, they should call him Jugler, if they were not taken away by <hi>3. September 1654.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But by the Instrument of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment your Protector hath his Negative voice in all things that oppose his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and such power in you the Militia and Navy, that nothing shall be done that doth not like him.</p>
                  <p>Through the Apostacy of this day they do now run in the name of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, as formerly in the name of the King, contrary to the former and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent desires of the Lords people, who then did, and now do, keep close to these honest Principles.</p>
                  <p>Why then are the true Patriots and Assertors of Right and Freedome kept in Prison, for above a year together, without any thing laid to their charge, seeing the face of an accuser, or being brought to a legal Tryall: Nay, some of them, their friends, scarce suffered to come and see them, and upon no other account, but because they presse to have these good things done, according to the very spirits of our desires in these Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What is become of this honest Heroick couragious spirit, for Righteousnesse, and breaking the Yoaks of Oppression, in which the Lord so owned you? Hath the Kings houses, Parks, and the great things of this world stopt your eares, and blinded
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115117:6"/> your eyes, that you cannot, or rather will not hear the cry of your brethrens bloud, nor the many declarations, remonstrances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the bringing forth those good things you seem so much to plead for, Are not the freedoms and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the people, as well worth the contending for as ever. Why do you not now with swords in your hands chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge these liberties, to live and dye for them against your Protector, the onely Grand Opposer of them, and beg your Collonells, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with the faithfull Patri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts &amp; people of the Nation, to give you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement and assistance for the accomplishment of these things, that so the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tions to come, may have just cause to blesse God for you.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>In a Letter to the Generall from divers Officers of the Army in the North, concerning the late large Petition presented to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nt, 11. <hi>Sept.</hi> 1648. aforementioned.</head>
               <p>Seeing that we and all the well affected of the Land, ventured our lives and all that was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ear unto us, not sparing cheerfully and faithfully, to passe through all dangers and difficulties with you, attending that Engagement. We are embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned now at last (having looked round about us, and finding neither your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, the Army, nor people yet answer a to those ends, to make our humble ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>resse to your Excellency in this juncture of time, wherein we apprehend, that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that hath been spilt, the Conquests that God hath crowned us withall, the treasure and wealth of the people expended, is all upon the point being ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in vain, and of none effect. For to the sorrow of our hearts, we finde that even those particulars of common Right and Freedom, for which we took up armes and stil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> continue them, are not regarded, though by way of humble Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ely presented to the House of Commons, by the well affected in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>London;</hi> and instead of answering their just desires of freedome, and safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the people, we finde a Treaty with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nquered Enemy is now chosen and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igorously carried on <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We having seriously weighed the foresaid Petition Intituled, <hi>The humble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tition of thousa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ds well affected persons, inhabiting the City of</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Westminster, <hi>the Borough of</hi> Southwark, <hi>Hamblets, and places adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent;</hi> presented to the Parliament <hi>11. September 1648.</hi> As also our dear Friends from the Garrisons of <hi>Newcastle</hi> and <hi>Tinmouth,</hi> and finding the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115117:6"/> common safety of us all wrapt up in these desires, we cannot in duty to God, to our own Native Countrey, and in Honour to your Excellencies safety, and all that have adheared to you, but resent the said desires as our own, and humbly implore, That your Excellency will be pleased so to appear before us in the cause of the people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That we and all the people with the Generations after us, by your Excellencies happy conduct, may have just cause to blesse God on your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition_excerpts">
               <head>Several of the chief passages contained in the large Petition, presented by thousands well affected persons inhabiting the City of <hi>London, Westminster, South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark,</hi> the Hamlets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> mentioned in the foregoing Letter.</head>
               <p>Be pleased to understand that we had not engaged on your part, but that we judged this honourable House to be the supreme Authority of England, as chosen by and representing the people, and entrusted with absolute power for redresse of grievances, and provision for safety, and that the K. was but at the most, the chief publick Officer of this Kingdom, and accountable to this House (the Representative of the people) from whom all just Authority is or ought to be derived for discharge of his Office: And if we had not been confident hereof, we had been despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately mad to have taken up Armes, or to have been ayding and assisting in maintaining a War against him, the Laws of the Land making it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly a Crime no lesse than Treason, for any to raise war against the King.</p>
               <p>But when we considered the manifold Oppressions brought upon the Nation by the King, &amp;c. and that it was evident that the King intended to raise forces and to make War, and that if he did set up his Standard, it tended to the dissolution of the Government: Upon this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the safety of the people to be above Law, and that to judge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of appertained to the supeam Authority, and not to the supream Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate; and being satisfied in our consciences, that the publik safety and freedome was in eminent danger, we concluded we had not onely just cause to maintain, but the supream Authority of the Nation to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie, defend, and indempnifie us in time to come, in what we should performe by direction thereof, though against the known Law of the Land, or any inferiour Authority though the highest. And as our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding was begot in us by principles of Right Reason, so were we cōfirmed therin by your own proceedings, as by your condemning those Judges who in the case of ship-money had declared the K. to be Judge of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115117:7"/> safety, and by your denying him a negative voyce in the making of Laws; where you wholly exclude the King from having any share in the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Authority: Then by your casting the Bishops out of the house of Lords, who by Tradition also had been accounted, an essential part of the supream Authority. And by your declaring to the Lords, that if they would not joyn with you in settling the Militia, you would set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle it without them, which you could not justly have done, had they had any reall share in the supream Authority.</p>
               <p>These things we took for reall demonstrations, that you undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knew your selves to be the supream Authority, ever weighing down in us all other your indulgent expressions, concerning the King or Lords, it being for us impossible to believe, that it can consist either with the safety or freedome of the Nation, either to be governed by three or two supreams, especially where experience hath approved them so apart to differ in their judgments concerning freedome, or safety, that the one hath bin know to punish, what the other hath judged wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of reward, when not onely the freedome of the people is directly opposite to the prerogative of Kings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whenas most of the oppressions of the Common-wealth, have in all times been brought upon the people by the King and Lords, who neverthelesse would be so equall in the supream Authority, as that there should be no redresse of grievances, no provision for safety, but at their pleasure, For our parts we professe our selves to be so far from judging this to be consistant with freedome, or safety, that we know not greater wherfore we assisted you in the late wars, but in hope to be delivered by you, from so intolerable, so destructive a bondage, so soon as you should (through Gods blessing upon the Armies raised by you) be enabled.</p>
               <p>But to our exceeding grief we have observed, that no sooner God vouchsafeth you victory, and blesseth you with successe, and thereby enableth you to put us and the whole Nation, in an absolute constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of freedome and safety, but according as ye have been accustomed, passing by the ruine of the Nation, and all the bloud that hath been spilt by the King and his party, ye betake your selves to a Treaty with him, thereby putting him that is but one single person, and a publick Officer of the Common-wealth, in competition with the whole body of the people whom ye represent, not considering that it is impossible for you to erect any Authority equall to your selves and declared to all the world, that you will not alter the Ancient Government from that of Kings, Lords, and Commons: Not once mentioning, in case of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115117:7"/> which of them is supream, but leaving that point (which was the chifest cause of all our publick differences, wars, and miseries) as uncertain as ever.</p>
               <p>In so much that we who upon these grounds have laid out our selves to the utmost of our abillities, and all throughout the land both Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and others, who have done the like in defence of your supream Authority, and in opposition to the King, cannot but deem our selves in the most dangerous condition of all others, left without all plea of indempnity for what we have done, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nor can we possibly conceive how any that have assisted you, can be any way exempted from the guilt of Murderers and Robbers, by the present Laws in force, if you persist to disclaim the supream Authority, though their own consciences ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit them, as having opposed none but manifest Tyrants, Oppressors, and their adherents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here followeth some particulars mentioned in the Petition, others being omitted for brevity sake.</p>
               <p>The truth is we have long expected things of another Nature from you, and such as we are confident would have given satisfaction to all serious people of all parties, As,</p>
               <p>First, that you would have made good the supream Authori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of the people in this honourable House from all pretences of Negative voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, either in King or Lords.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that you would have made Laws for election of Represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives, yearly, and of course, without Writ or Summons.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that you would have set expresse tearms for their meeting, continuance, and dissolution, as not to exceed fourty or fifty dayes at the most, and to have fixed an expresse time for the ending of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Parliament.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that you would have exempted matters of Religion and Gods Worship, from the compulsive or restrictive power of any Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity upon earth, and reserved to the supream Authority an uncompul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive power onely of appointing a way for the publick, whereby abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of misery, persecutions, and heart burnings, would for ever be avoided.</p>
               <p>Eightly, that you would have freed all men from being examined against themselves, and from being questioned or punished for doing that, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ainst which no law hath been provided.</p>
               <p>Sixteenthly, that you would have removed the tedious burden of Tythes, satisfying all Impropriators, and providing a more equal way of maintenance for the Publick Ministers.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115117:8"/>
               <p>The things and worthy Acts that have been done, and achieved by this Army and their adherents (however ing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atfully suffered to be scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dallized, as Secta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies and men of corrupt judgments) in defence of the just Authority of this honourable House, and of the common Liberties of the Nation, and in opposition to all kind of Tyrany and Oppression, being so far from merriting in odious Act of Oblivion, that they rather deserve a most honourable Act of perpetual Remembrance, to be as a patterne of publick vertue, fidelity, and resolution to all posterity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <head>A Gratulatory Letter from divers Officers of the Army at the League before <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wick,</hi> to the late Presentors of the large Petition of <hi>Sept. 11. 1648.</hi>
               </head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Gentlemen and fellow Commoners.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>As we all languish and groan under the insupportable weight of the pubick oppression of the land, so it is our duty to strugle and strive joyntly together, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of each other, for to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour we are bound as to our selves, and we are all the sonnes of one Nation, and Brethren by nature, whose several weale and woe, is included and wrapt up in the fold of one common-wealth, that we must even stand and fall together. We (though we have our swords in our hands) cannot be without you, nor you without us, in this day of publick calamity; and of this (we do not question but) as we with you, so you with us, are suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently sensible, which to all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciencious and juditious men, may be sufficient to tye us firmly toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one common bond of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, against all our Oppressors and Opposers of freedome whatsoever
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115117:8"/> But in this we give you the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence, for though we are with you in heart and affection, for the principles of cōmon right &amp; free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the Land; yet we must give you the right hand of fellowship, in appearing and going before us therein; for the great refresh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our spirits, we finde that God hath preserved yet thousands for us, that have not bowed their knee to <hi>Baal,</hi> and are yet (after all these afflictions and tryals) firme and untainted with the poisonous principles of Oppress<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on and Tyranny, as by your two late Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ions appeareth; for which we are bound in duty to render the glory there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of unto God, so in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>umane and civil obligation, we cannot but ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our gratefull and cordial respects unto you for the same, and must professe it our duty to attest the same wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> our sword<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, in, and for those just principles (in your Petit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ined) to live and die with you and for you.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>From the Leagure before</hi> Barwick <date>Sept. 30. 1648.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>Have you by writing and printing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged &amp; invited the faithfull in the land, to stand by and own you with their p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rsons, purses, &amp; prayers, pretending to be one with them in pressing for, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring after their Rights, and Freedomes, in the way of a Common-wealth, opposed to the interest of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch or single person, commending their forwardnesse theirin, blessing the Lord he had kept them from bowing their knee to <hi>Baal, viz.</hi> the principles of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and Oppression, as if you abhorred i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and did never intend so much as to think of entering into, or to be uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the practise of such principles your selves. And do you after your own turn are served, deceive them in the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up or in maintaining when up, the very same Interests, Tyranny, and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, of a single person in your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector. Thou that sayest, another should not bow to <hi>Baal,</hi> and doest so thy self, thy condemnation is jus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; these things considered, you are concerned to look a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115117:8"/> you, and as you were then ready with swords in your hands, to stand by the faithfull of the land, in and for those just principles contained in their Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to live and dye for them, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position to the King. So it behoves you to be as ready to do the same against your Protector, who more opposes these good things now, than the King did then, lest that this bloud of your friends which hath been shed upon, and after those incouraging words, be fruitlesse and in vain, and the guilt thereof be charged upon you.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <head>In an other Declaration of the Generall and Council of warr, they say as followes:</head>
               <p>And if when this Kingdome hath spent so much of its bloud and treasure, hath past through such un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eard of dangers, &amp; overcome such difficulties so many years toget<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, all that they must now h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pe for, and rest in, must onely be what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ing gran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in his Message of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. of <hi>May</hi> last, and if this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>st be i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n mens judgments and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences by an Oath, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into in a tumultuous and unlawfull way, and by out<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>age
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115117:9"/> maintained in despight and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Parliament: If, rather than this should not be accomplish- the Parliament must be violated and forced into the hands of such of the Members thereof, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly abetted and fomented those practises to that end, that these hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den councels and works of darknes, might when they come to their full birth, have the Image of highest Authority in the face of them, the better to gain credit thereunto, and secure the Authors, of them from punishment. If these tings we say must be the end and upshot of all, what then remains to this poor Kingdome and all true hearted Englishmen, but to joyn together as one man, with their counsells, estates, and lives, in this way as our last refuge under God, which he by his wise and gracious providence hath reserved and provided, by keeping up this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, even to a Myracle, so to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the aforesaid evils, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to this dying Kingdome, yet a settled peace and happinesse.</p>
               <p>These things being seriously con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered by us, we have thought fit in the name of the Army, to declare that all such Members of either house of Parliament, as are already with the Army, for the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of their persons, and for the ends aforesaid, are forced to absent themselves from <hi>Westminster.</hi> That we all hold and esteem them as persons in whom the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115117:9"/> publick trust of the Kingdome is still remaining, though they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not for the present sit as a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with freedome and safety at <hi>Westminster;</hi> and by whose advice and counsel, we desire to govern our selves in, in the managing these weighty affaires, and to that end we invite them to make repair to the Army, to joyn with us in this great cause, we b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing resolved, and do hereby faithfully oblige our selves to stand by them therein, and to live and dye with them against all opposition whatsoever, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>And may not we take up the same complaint, and say; And if when this Nation hath spent so much bloud and Treasure, and overcome such difficulties for so many yeares together, First, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Tyranny of the King and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether therewith, the Acts and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Parliament, and your Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations against Mona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chy it self, and for a Common-wealth, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d would have no Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>; and yet after all this for your Generall, out of his desire of domin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion to as<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to himself, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115117:9"/> impose upon us the very same forme of Government and more Tyrannicall and Arbitrary than the former, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than this shall not be accomplished, first, the old Parliament must be broken, upon pretence they would do no good but perpetuate themselves, and when the little Parliament was chosen, and were doing these good things the others were turned out for not doing, a party of them for his interest, must early in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning before the others could get together, without putting it to a Vote, in a chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting manner, go away with their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended power to him, and the others who stayed behinde, turned out in a violent manner, by some of you (as Reforma- does and Prentices by the instigation of those corrupt Members you here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of, made those of the Parliament, who would not joyn with them, fly to the Army for shelter) That so these hidden counsels and works of darknesse, might have the Image of the highest Authority upon the face of them, the better to gain credit thereunto. If these things we say must be the end and upshot of all (which is worse than what the King stood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in his Message of the <hi>12.</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> what then remains to all true hearted Englishmen, but (according to your advice in the like case) to joyn together as one man with their councels, estates, and lives, in this way as our last refuge under God, to hinder the progresse of the aforesaid Tiranny, and to procure to this Nation its just and lawfull Rights, and Freedomes, and in order thereunto, to call unto their assistance such persons, who were turned out of the little Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115117:9"/> and have not since defiled their garments, and such of the old Parliament with others, whose hearts are faithfull withall, who fear the Lord, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue friends to justice and liberty, and haters of tyranny, and to esteem them as persons in whom the publick trust of the Nation is still of right remaining and to be governed by their advice and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell, in managing the weighty affairs, and resolve to stand by them therein, and to live and dye with them against all opposition whatsoever. Surely this may as honestly be done against your Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls upstart Government, as for you to have done the same against the King, and that corrupt party in the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament whom you so opposed in that day.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <head>In the case of the Army stated and proposed by the agents of five Regiments of horse (<hi>viz.</hi> Lievtenant Generalls, Commissary Generalls, Collonel <hi>Fleetwoods</hi> Collonell <hi>Riches,</hi> Collonell <hi>Whaleys,</hi>) to their respective Regiments and the whole Army, and presented to the Generall Sr. <hi>Thomas Fairfax Oct. 15. 1647.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 4. <hi>say they,</hi> It is declared in the Armies Declaration 14. <hi>June</hi> 1647. that the Army took up armes in judgement and conscience for the peoples just rights and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and not as Mercinary soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers hired to serve the Arbitrary power of the State and that in the same manner it continu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s at that time.</p>
               <p>And in <hi>Page</hi> 7. of ihe same de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, it was declared, they proceeded upon the principles of right and Freedome, and upon the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115117:10"/> law of nature and Nations. But the strength of the endeavours of many hath been and are now spent to perswade the souldiers and agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators, that they stand as souldiers onely to serve the State, and may not as free commoners, claim their freedome as due to them, as those ends for which they have hazzarded thir lives, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 6. In Declaration 14. <hi>June Page</hi> 10. as in all other Remonstran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and declarations it was desired that the rights and liberties of the people might be secured, before the Kings businesse should be consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But now the grievances of the people are propounded to be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered after the restoring him to the Regal Power, and that in such a way according to the proposals, <hi>viz.</hi> with a Negative voice, that the people that have purchased by bloud what was their right, of which the King endeavoured to deprive them, should yet solely depend on his will for relief in their grievances and Oppressions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It hath been alwaies profest and declared that the Army was called forth, and conjured by the Parliaments Declarations for defence of the peoples just rights, against the forces raised by the King.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>When that corrupt party both in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Army told you, you onely served the State for wages, &amp; might not as free commoners claim your freedomes as your due upon hazzard of your lives: You then could quote severall declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to manife t you engaged not as Mercinary Souldiers, but for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples rights, yet now notwithstanding, your G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nerall deprives us of the same rigbts which they endeavoured to do, and hath his negative voice and all things concerning the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lief of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples grievances more under his own di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spose
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115117:10"/> than ever the King had, and you can be silent as if that honest spirit you seem here to be acted by were dead or was never truly breathing in you.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>Whereas it is now many months since the Army declared, that they would insist upon the peoples inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest as in Declaration 14. <hi>June</hi> P. 13. and yet no relief for the people in any of their Oppressions by Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary powers, Monopolies, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice in the proceeding at Law. Tythes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is effectually procured nor any greater probability of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture help is visible than was before, no foundations of freedom being yet l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id, and yet the souldery bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens the countrey, and occasions great taxes, upon which these five mischiefs follow.</p>
               <p>I shalll onely mention some of them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The love and affecton of the people to the Army is decayed,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115117:10"/> cooled, and near lost; its already the common voice of the people, what good hath our new saviours done for us? what grievance have they procured to be redressed? wherein is our condition bettr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, or how are we more free than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>&amp;c?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Whiles the peoples old Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions are continued, and more Taxes are imposed for pay of the Army, they are disabled daily more &amp; more for the maintenance of an Army for their preservation, for they begin to say, they can but be destroyed by Oppress<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, and its all one to them, whether it be by pretended friends or professed ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, it were a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good say they, that the King should rule again by prerogative, we were slaves then to his will, and we are now no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, we had rather have one Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant than hundreds.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Page</hi> 9. By this means the people are inclined to tumults, crying out, will none procure relief for us? Shall we alwaies be delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with fair words, and be devoured by professors? we must 'ere long rise up in armes, and every one catch what he can, thus confusion is threatened.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Many Souldiers are asham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d of themselves and fear that the people should rise to destroy them; you will do nothing for us (say they) we are vexed by Malignant Judges for conscience sake, by arbitrary Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees in the countrey, and at Parliament Ordering one thing to day, and recalling it the next; injustice in the Law is the same, and we buy our right at as dear a rate as ever, Tythes are inforced from us double and treble, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 10 They thought (<hi>viz</hi> the old Parliament) we would have stood as Mercenary Souldiers hired to serve their Arbitrary Power, and not remembred that we by their invitation took up armes in judgement
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115117:11"/> and conscience, to preserve the Nation from Tyranny and Oppression, and therefore were obliged to insist upon our rights and freedoms, as Commoners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and upon this ground we judge the Parliament hath proceeded of late, to encrease the peoples Oppressions, by an Ordinance for treble damages to be paid by all that refuse (though for consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence sake) to pay Tythes, and an Ordinanc to look up the Printing Presses against whom they please, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ich was in the Bishops time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of as one of the great Oppressions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <p>And may not we say, its some years past, since you declared you would not disband till you saw the foundations of the peoples freedomes and liberties surely laid, and yet we are further off than when you sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke these words, for thorough the Oppression and Tyranny of your Generall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Monopolies, as formerly are encouraged, not onely in Merchandize and other things, but upon the Scriptures also, insomuch that a Bible is not now to be had unlesse we pay ten pence more than formerly they were sold for, And this your Master doth to encourage his Printers to turn Cachpoles and to be the more diligent in the suppressing of that truth (chiefly) which discovers his Hypocricy, neither can any man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ept he own his usurpt power, have benefit of the law, and is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115117:10"/> so tyrannicall, that no Lawyer dare▪ plead in a cause again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t him though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so just, as our experience can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. These things considered with his imprisoning the Saints for non pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Tythes, and their not comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him, but opposing his declen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from those honest principles you here so much declare for, with many other grievances now lying upon us and likely to be continued by your closing with him, and yet notwithstanding, great Taxes continued for your pay, No won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if you have lost the peoples love, and they as formerly do ask, where is the good the Army hath done us after their large professions which is now no more than in change of the person, and in taking off <hi>Charls</hi> his yoa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, to keep on <hi>Olivers;</hi> Now if upon their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eing thus deluded, they contrive how to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver themselves, and Tumults do rise upon this account, then consider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by these words, you do not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that Oppressors and Tyran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s are the causers of it.</p>
                  <p>Anot.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And is not this Ordinance for treble damages renued by your General and such who for conscience sak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> refuse to pay Tythes more violently persecuted than ever, to the imprisonment of some, and undoing of others, as ulso the Printing Presses upon all occasions diligently searcht, and a strict charge laid upon the Printers, least any thing come fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th to manifest the back-sliding of this day; I forbare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o name the Over-seers of this work, or where they are related, least the true s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed among them suffer for their sakes; but when such persons come to do the devils work, for the riches and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>onour of this world, its high time to searce Jerusalem with candles, they are as evident suppressors of truth, as ever the Bishops and their pandors were in that day, which will be proved to their faces if they dare stand the tryall.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 13. Through the Armies declining its first principles to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist upon satisfaction and security as Souldiers and Commoners be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore disbanding, or deviding, the Army is now likely to be so farr scattered into several quarters, that it shall be in no capacity to insist upon security for arrears, suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent indempni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, or any of its own or the Nations rights, in case they shall be still denyed them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 13. Its to be considered that the enemies on the one hand, and the other encrease daily in their confidence and strength, whilest security for the Armies ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears and constant future pay are not provided, and the rights and freedomes of the people are not cleared and secured, and the Army
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115117:11"/> may devide in case one part should insist upon the first just principles, and be faithfull thereunto, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other part should by flatteries, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments, fear, or negligence, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline or desert them, and let it be considered how far this will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the ruine of the Army and Kingdome.</p>
               <p>We never did nor do regard the worst of evils or mischiefs that can befall o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r selves, in comparison of the consequence of them to the poor Nation, or to the security of common right and freedome, we could not but in reall, not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall trouble of heart for the poor Nation and oppressed people, break forth and cry, O our bowels! our bowells! we are troubled at the very heart, to hear the peoples dolefull groans, and yet their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected deliverers will not hear, or consider; they have run too and fro, and sighed or even wept forth their sorrowes and miseries in Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition first to King, then to Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and then to Army; yet they all have been like broken reeds, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Army it self on whom they leaned, have peirced their hands, their eyes, even failed with look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for peace and freedome, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold nothing but Oppression, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straction and trouble, <hi>&amp;c</hi> We wish therefore the bowells of compassion, of the whole Army, might yearn towards their distressed Brethren, and that they might with one consent say each to other, Come let us joyn together speedily, to demand present redresse for the peoples grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and security for all their and our rights and freedomes, as souldiers and commoners, let us never devide each from other, till those just de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115117:12"/> be answered really and effectually, that so for the peoples ease, as many forces as are not absolutely necessary, may be speedily dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded, and our honour may be preserved unspoted, when they shall see that we minded not our own interest, but the good fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dome and wellfare of the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Nation.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <p>It seems that corrupt party before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned in Parliament and Army, did designe and endeavour to quarter the Army at such a distance from one another, that wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n they come to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, you might not be in a capacity to insist upon those good things, for which you took up armes at fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, the consideration whereof▪ and the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ruin which was like to come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Nation, if this design had taken, did seemingly so affect your hearts, that you could not bear it, but cryed out, O your B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w lls! your Bowells! and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest to be so carefull of the peoples rights, as if you mind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d their security more than your own, and complain, that the King and Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>liament had failed them like broken re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ds, yea the Army it s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lf, on whom they had leaned, had peirced th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir hands, but your selves to be such
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115117:11"/> friends as would never leave them till their rights and liberties were secured, by which good words and fair speeches they were drawn away to be so simple, and sinfull as to leane upon you, who like broken reeds have peirced their hands as well as they you so complain of; for instead of taking away their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions and providing for their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, you keep on the one, and obstruct the other. And therefore if you would approve your selves to the Lord and his people, that you have minded his glory and their good more than your own, and would engage their hearts again unto you, then bring forth fruit worthy of repentance, and say in heart as well as words, Come Brethren and fellow Commoners, the truth is, you have lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned too much upon us, and therefore it is just with the Lord, for this sinne of yours, and our too much minding our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears and futu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e pay, the favour of men and our worldly concernments, that we have so deceived you hitherto, but seeing our evil, we are resolved in the the streng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h of the Lord, if you will joyn with us, we will never devide any more from you, till this beastly founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with its tyranny, be thrown down, and those good things brought forth, we have formerly so declar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d for, for we plainly see we shall never be right till we come to this.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>Now to all that shall thus appear we propound,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 14. That whatsoever was porposed to be insisted upon either in Declaration of <hi>June</hi> 14. or the Remonstrance of <hi>June</hi> 23. and in the Remonstrance from <hi>Kingston August</hi> 18. be adheared to resolvedly, so as not to recede from those desires, untill they be throughly and effectually answered: More particularly that whereas it appears by positive Laws, and ancient just customes, that the people have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> right to new successive elections for Parliaments, at certain periods of time, and that it ought not to be denyed them, being so essentiall to their freedome, that without it they are no better than slaves, the nature of that legislative power being arbitrary, and that therefore it be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted on so possitively and resolvedly, as not to recede from it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 15. Whereas Parliaments rightly constituted, are the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our hopes of right and freedome to this people, and whereas the people have been prevented of Parliaments, though many positive laws have been made for a constant succession of Parliaments, that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be possitively and resolvedly infisted upon, that a law paramount be made, enacting it to be unalterable by Parliaments, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple shall of course meet without any Writ or Warrants, once in every two years, on an appointed day in their respective Counties, for the electiton of their Representors in Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Although this case of the Army stated, with some Letters and other things contained in this collection, do come onely in the names of some particular Troops, or Regiments, yet the Agent were encouraged therein by your Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, who was then Lievtenant Generall, and some other Officers of the Army, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> (in tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> day) more eminently appeared for righteousnesse, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest Sectarian part of the pepople of God, than others, and have nothing in them, but what doth center in, and agree with, the Remonstrance at</hi> Albon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>the agreement with the people, and with the tree Acts of Parliament com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming after, which the Army approved of, and consented to, and what might be spoken as to Parliaments in this place, I referr you to them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115117:12"/>
               <p>Wereas all power is originally and essentially in the whole body of the people of this Nation, and whereas their free choise or consent by their Representors, is the onely originall or foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all just government; and the reason and end of the choise of all just Governors whatsoever, is their apprehension of safety and good by them, that it be insisted upon positively, that the supream power of the peoples Representors or Commons ass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbled in Parliament, be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with clearly declared as their power to make Laws, or repeal Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as also their power to call to an account all Officers of this Nation whatsoever, for their neglects, or their treacheries in their trust for the peoples good, and to continue or remove them from their Offices according to their demerrits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And further, that this power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute any kinde of Governors or Officers, that they shall judge for the peoples good, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This power of Commons in Parliament, is the thing against which the King hath contended, and the people have defended with their lives, and therefore ought now to be demanded as the price of their bloud.</p>
               <p>They say the Generals answer was, that he judged their intentions were honest, and desired that every one of a publick spirit would be acting for the publick, and that for his part he had freely ventured his life for common right and freedome, and should freely engage it again; adding further, that he thought it meet it should be presented to the Generall Councill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <head>In the Remonstance of the Army at <hi>Albons 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>1648.</hi> presented to the Commons assembled in Parliament the <hi>20.</hi> following.</head>
               <p>The summe of the publick interest of a Nation in relation to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon right and freedome (which hath been the chief subject of our contest) and in opposition to tyranny and injustice to Kings, or others, we take to lye in these things following,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That for all matters of supream trust or concernment to the safety and welfare to rhe whole, they have a Commons and supream Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell or Parliament, and that (as to the common behalf, who cannot all meet together themselves) to consist of Deputies or Representors freely chosen by them, with as much equallity as may be, and those electi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons to be successive and renewed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If the only probable way for the preservation of common right and freedome
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115117:13"/> in opposition to the tyranny and injustice of Kings or others be, that all matter, of supream Tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t and Concernment for publique welfare should be in the hands of the peoples Deputies or Representors, freely, and successively chosen. Then surely your contest with the King, and shedding so much bloud, hath either been upon wrong and mistaken grounds, or else you are become most fearful Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states, in forsaking this probable way, and upholding this power in the hands of your Generall as a single person and his Councell, as it was before in the King.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p n="2">2. That the power of making Laws Constitutions and Offices (for the preservation and concernment of the whole) and of altering or repealing and a bolishing the same (for removal of any publick grievance therein) and the power of finall judgement concerning war or peace, the safety and welfare of the people, and all civil things wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tsoever, without further appeals to any created standing power, and the supream Trust in relation to all such things, may rest in that supream Counsell so as,</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Contrary to the grave intent and spirit of this particular, this power doth now recide in a Protector, and a Parliament, as it did formerly in a King and Parliament as appears</hi> Instr. Gov. <hi>Article</hi> 1. <hi>which power your Generall hath assumed to himself, purely for support of his Interest, and to keep the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in his own hand, which he could not well do, without li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>king up the old vomit, and treading in the formerly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>rown-up paths of tyranny and oppression, he and you had been so instru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>all to destroy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p n="1">1. That the ordinary ordering &amp; government of the people may be by such Offices, and Administrations, and according to such Laws, and Rules, as by that Council or the Representative body of the people therein have been prescribed or allowed, and not otherwise.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That none of those extraordinary or arbitrary powers afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, may be exercised towards the people by any as of right, but by that supream Council or by the Representative body of the people therein, nor without their advice or consent, may any thing be imposed upon or taken from the people, or if it be otherwise at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temped that the people are not bound thereby, but free, and the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempter punishable.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That those extraordinary powers or any of them, may be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised by that supream Councill, or by the Representative body of the people therein, and where they shall see cause to assume and exercise the same, in a matter which they finde necessary for the safety or well-being
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115117:13"/> of the people, their proceedings and determinations therein may be binding and conclusive to the people, and to all Officers of Justice, and Ministers of State whatsoever: And that it may not be left in the will of the King, or any particular persons (standing in their own interest) to oppose, make voide, or render ineffectuall, such their determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or proceedings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>Contrary to the intent and purport of these three particulars, hath your Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rased down these foundations of right and freedome, usurping this power into his own hand, as chief Magistrate and his Councill, as appears <hi>Iust. Gov.</hi> Articles <hi>2. 3.</hi> And if your will say it is in a Parliament too, its answered they bear but the name without the power, for at his lust and pleasure, if they own not his Government they are shut cut; and if they do own it, and do not Act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will and interest, they are dissolved. And you Souldiers, that force the people to pay Taxes, and uphold your Master whilest he arbitrarily and of his own head, layes impositions upon the estates of your friends, decimates the revenues of others without, or contrary to any Law establisht by the peoples Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentors, according to your own words are worthy of punishment, and the people not obliged to such impositions, but may freely resist.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 16. These things contain the summe or main of publick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, and as they are the ordinary subject of civil contests, in all mixt States, where they happen be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wixt the people and those who have as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed or claimed a standing pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge or prerogative over them; so they have been in this of ours. And against these maters of publick intrest, this King hath all along (his reign) opposed, and given himself up to uphold and advance the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of his and his Posterities will and power; First that there might be no such common Councill (no Parliaments) at all to restrain or check him, but that all these mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of supream Trust, concerning safety and all things else, might rest
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115117:14"/> rest in him and in his brest alone, without limit from, or acccount to any in earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 17. To support himself in that state or height of tyranny, and make it absolute, he raised his first and second armes against his people in both Kingdomes, when he found he could not keep up to that height to have all those extraordinary powers, and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of trust in himself alone, then he fell to play lower, that at least none of them might be exercised by any without him, no not by all the Trustees of the land, nor in any case, tho never so necessary for the relief or saving of the people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And for this when the Parliament did otherwise assume, in point of immediate safety, &amp; punishment of Delinquents without him) he rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed his third armes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And though he raised with the pretense onely of opposing the execise of those ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary and arbitrary powers, by your selves or any other with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him (which would not be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed himself to exercise alone, yet in the raising and having raised that force, he did by it assume and exercise all kinds of absolute and arbitrary powers at his own will alone without Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But when (his other claims so far falling) it came to this, he that before would not have allowed the the Parliament or Kingdome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer for safety, but at his will, would (at least) make you know,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115117:14"/> that not you, nor the Kingdome, should have any peace or quiet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, and that neither Parliament nor any power on earth (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever ills he had done, might for it attach, or meddle with his facred person, and for this last part of his Interest his fourth Armes was raised 1648. the Scotch invasion was procured, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 21. That where a person trusted with a limited power to Rule according to Laws, and by his trust (with expresse Covenant and Oath also) obliged to preserve and protect the Rights and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the people, for, and by whom he is entrusted, shall not onely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert that Trust, and abuse that power, to the hurt and prejudice of the generallity, and to the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression (if not destruction of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, but also by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the trust and power he hath) shall rise to the ass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ming of hurtfull powers never committed to him? and indeed to take away all those foundations of Right and Liberties, and of redresse and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy too, which the people had reserved from him, and to swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low up all into his absolute will and power, to impose or take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, yea, to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stroy at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, and declining all appeale herein, to the established equall judgement (agreed upon as it were betwixt him and his people, in all immergent matters of difference betwixt them) or to any judgment of men at all, shall flye to the way of force upon his trusting people, and attempt by it to uphold and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablish himself in that absolute tyrannicall power so assumed over
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115117:15"/> them and in the exercise thereof at pleasure, such a person in so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, doth forfeit all that trust and power he had, and (absolving the people from the bonds of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant &amp; peace betwixt him &amp; them) does set them free to take their best advantage, and (if he fall wirhin their power) to proceed in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment against him even for that alone if there were no more, and to make this good they quote <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3. where they say <hi>Paul</hi> speaks of Magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in its constitution (not of a person abusively exercising it) to be Gods instrument for good to every one, therefore the Kings of the Israelites must know the Law for a rule <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 11.12. <hi>David</hi> in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. avoucheth a rule for all Rulers, he that ruleth among men, must be just, ruling in the fear of God: The people set free to take the best ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to proceed in judgement against him, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.10. <hi>Josh.</hi> 21.13. This in the <hi>Abridg. Remonst.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 23. 24. (say they) For any King to take up Armes, or in any other way endeavour to uphold the interest of his will &amp; power against the common interest of his people, such a person may be justly said to be guilty of the highest Treason, against the highest Law amongst men, &amp; that the publick justice of a Nation cannot be satisfied, the bloud avenged, the wrath of God for the same appeased, without judgement executed against h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. For this they quote <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.4. <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.13. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.5 6.14.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <p>If the summe or main of publick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest is conteined in this, that in all matters of publick concernment, the trust thereof should be in the peoples Representors, and not in a single person and his Councill, and if it were so ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall in the King, for the advance of his interest, to endeavour to make voide the power of Parliaments, so as they should not check or restrain him from having this trust resting in him alon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, without limitation or giving account to any on earth; and there having been so much bloud shed in our contest against these things, then how can you but blush, when you consider that your Generall doth the very same things? plucking up by the roots the very summe and main of publick inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, placing it so in his own brest, that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115117:14"/> nothing can be done without him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are brought under greater slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry than in the day of the King.</p>
                  <p>You opposed the King first because he assumed that trust wholly to himself, which of right should be in the peoples Representors: And <hi>2.</hi> when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desended so low, as to give way they should have the exercise thereof, yet so as not without him; you would not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of that, but maintained the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in their exercising this trust without him, because yee judged it most safe to publick Interest: yet the same power you denyed to him, your Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rall hath assumed to himself, and you uphold him in it, whereby we are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slaved to his arbitrary will and lust, as the King endeavoured to do in that day; and although he doth not say (as he did) that no lawfull power on earth ought to attach or meddle with him, for this or any other evil; yet by his power in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Militia, and Navy, he hath so strengthened him self, that except the Lord do wonderfully step in to deliver us, we shall be kept under a perpetui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y of slavery and bondage; for his saying he will lay down his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> bones in uphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his usurpt Government, declares plainly he designes to perpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uate his oppression upon us. But as the former Tyrants Charrot wheels wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by degrees taken off till he came down to the block, so the disappointments the Lord gives your Master in his undertakings ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his abasement, are sad presages that if he persist to walk in the Kings steps, he must partake of his punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115117:14"/>
                  <p>Now if a lawfull Magistrate doing thus, forfeits all that power and trust he had, and sets the people free from the bonds of Covenant and Peace between them, to take their best ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to proceed in judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, if this might be done to the green tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, <hi>viz.</hi> a lawfull power, then what will become of your drye Protector an unlawfull power, neither chosen nor entrusted by God nor the people, but hath meerly usurpt it, and rooted up these very foundations of right and freedome, setting up his Arbitrary lust above all law, and is so strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and upheld in your assistance in this Tyranny, that the supream Authority, the peoples Rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>esentors, cannot come together with freedome, to call him to account, nor dare any other Court of Judicature proceed against him to give redresse in these things. Wherefore by your own words, the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ople are free from subjection to such a usurpt power as his is▪ and may take their best ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage when they shall have opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to throw off his Yoak, and bring him to condigne punishment: And so much the rather, because he hath bin formerly so great an A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sertor of these Liberties for the people, in opposition to this Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and Oppress<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on in the King. Now for him after all, to tread in the very same and broader paths of Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Oppression, for the advance of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115117:15"/> his private interest, surely his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and condemnation must needs be much more righteous, and the publick justice of the Nation, and the wrath of God con lesse be satisfied or appeased, if there be not a proceeding against him, for if Scripture will justifie the former, the latter will be much more clear and without exception.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <head>
                  <hi>And in the</hi> 8. <hi>and</hi> 9. <hi>Pages of the Abridgment of this Remonstrance, they hold forth its dangerous to receive the King unto tearms of agreement and peace,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>And after this accommodation to s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tisfie the people, you shall disbād your forces, you are at the Kings curtesie still, and are but where you were at fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st, but the King in much fairer possibility to revive the old quarrell, and carry it without fighting, for after so much bloud and trouble for nothing, it is not like you will finde a competent party for the opposing of him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Besides these we cannot but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115117:15"/> the vast possibilities after his restitution, to make or use factions among your selves, and your adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and do not all men acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him most exquisite at it, &amp; if h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had that faculty to avayl at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, much more in your bosoms, each party will be apt to strive, which shall most, and first comply with him, of which y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u and we have seen sad experiences already, yet we refus'd ought of private con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tract or trust with him &amp; his, &amp; all was with saving for the publi{que} In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To conclude we confess our fears from the Act of this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments unlimited continuance, if he forme a ballancing party in the house of Commons for his Interest, that which should be our conserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive would be our bain, and yet we should be debared from change of Medicine, or if a period be set to this Parliament, and no provision for certain suecession, and sitting of Parliaments; withous dependance on the Kings will, or if no provisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for a more due consti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ution, by more equall elections, than the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess will be les hopefull, &amp; safe then the present, and you have not in this Treaty made any provision for these things; but to proceed to sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w the certain insecurity to publiq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e interest, in accommodation with a r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stitution of the King, for you the supream Judicature of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (when he is in your power to do justice upon) to decline that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, and instead thereof, to seek to him your prisoner in way of Treaty, what speaks it lesse, than that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he is indeed above all humane Justi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, not accountable to, or punishable by any power on ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, whatsoever he doth, and that Kings cannot erre or do wrong, whereas
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115117:16"/> one example of this kinde made, would be of more terrour and avail, than the execution of his whole party, yea, than all satisfaction you can imagine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>If it were so probable that the King who had so much lost the love of the Parliament and people in his raising a war and shedding of bloud, would have gained su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h a party to his interest as might undoubtedly have been to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick prejudice, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n much more will a single person in that power gain upon them, who (though indeed he be more) yet is not so seemingly blame-worthy as the King was, so that by this
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115117:15"/> foregoing and what comes after in the Remon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>trance, as als<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by the Act of Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>liament <hi>17.</hi> of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 1648</hi> for the abolishing of Kingly Government, and your declaration in <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp;c. That you judged it most safe to publ que Intere t, that the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion should be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by the peoples R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntors suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>siv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly chosen, without a single person and his Councill. Now if not only from natural wisedom, but that which is spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual also, you would contend so ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly for publick Libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ty against Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, how comes it th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n to passe you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t so contrary now? Su <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly that glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of the Lord with you (when ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to be acted by this cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest spirit) compared with his eminent departing f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om you, since your very fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t declension from it, to act upon the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al foundation, declares plainly he approves not of your actions. And whereas you say it would be our bain to want provision for certain succession and equall elections, of the peoples Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in case the King had been received and invested with that power over Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>liaments which he had so much contended for. Is it not as mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive to the peoples Lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rty, for you to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntain the same power in your Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, which you then judged so perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> King?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>For just laws being from God <hi>(Themis</hi> the daughter of <hi>Jove)</hi> who is not under them, owns not his subjection to God, whereas God hath not put that distance betwixt Kings and other men, they are his brethren though his subjects, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17 ult. so <hi>David</hi> calls his subjects, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.2. if any King, because a King, be punishable by men, then all Kings are so, and no man may justly punish any King: But when a people to be punisht shall spare their King, as <hi>Saul</hi> (the people then admiring happily the persons, aswell as government of Kings) spared <hi>Agagg, Sam.</hi> 15.9. But we find Gods instruments fixing more solemne punishments on wicked Kings, than on their wicked peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Joshua</hi> slaies all their Kings, <hi>Josh.</hi> 11.17. being thirty one, 11. <hi>ch.</hi> vlt. and hangs up some, <hi>Josh.</hi> 10.24, 28, 30, 40. <hi>Mideon</hi> more so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly executes the Kings of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dean, then other enemies, <hi>Judg</hi> 8.5, 21. <hi>Ehud</hi> slayes King <hi>Eylon. Judg.</hi> 3.21. so <hi>Jehoiadah</hi> and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders put <hi>Athaliah</hi> to death 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.14. And if it be said these two last Princes came to the crown by force and bloud, and so were without a title, it may be replyed, that such was the ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the first of the English, French, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Royall race, from whom the present Kings claim, but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115117:16"/> further, these two had reigned, and the people been subjects to them (which makes the most usuall Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle) the one for 18. years, <hi>Judges</hi> 3.14. the other 6. years, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.12. <hi>Jehu</hi> did slay both the Kings of Israell, and <hi>Judah</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9. And <hi>Asaph</hi> prayes <hi>Psalm.</hi> 83.11. that Nobles and Princes of enemies, may be used after former examples, and as this rank of men is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing Christ in the last times, so are they by him, and his people to be punished, <hi>Psal.</hi> 2. <hi>Psal.</hi> 110.5. The Lord at thy right hand shall strike thorough Kings in the day of thy wrath, <hi>Psal.</hi> 149.8, 9. to bind their Kings in chains, and Nobles in fetters of Iron, to execute upon them the judgement written this honour have the Saints, the fowls are invited to eat the flesh of kings, and captaines are slaughtered by the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.17, 18. It could not have been without scandall, if <hi>David</hi> had slain <hi>Saul</hi> because a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate person, and under personall hate and injury, it would have sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured of ambition or revenge; And it was onely declared against the succeeding of his Race, not the continuance of his person, but the state and people, not taking course against <hi>Saul,</hi> did smart in his other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of punishment. It appears <hi>David</hi> forbore him not meerly out of Reverence to his Authority, for he took up armes to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self against him, and would (if that part of people would have joyned) have maintained <hi>Kailah</hi> against him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23 Now all this was co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to subjection, and intimates that if <hi>David</hi> had been put to it, and he could not otherwise have escaped, would have used force against <hi>Saul,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 10. <hi>Abridg. Remonst.</hi> They do fully acknowledge the power to be in the peoples Representatives in Parliament, and that the executing of justice and shewing mercy was in them.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115117:16"/>
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>If you might honestly bring these Scriptures as examples and rules, to encourage and stir up the Parliament to execute justice upon the King, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured by force to uphold himself in that tyrannicall power he assumed over the Nation, and laid so much weight thereon, that you as it were told them if they refused you would do it your selves. Then why may not we whose hearts, purses, and prayers, were engaged with you in that work, and yet thorough grace are kept faithful to those honest principles, as honestly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose your Generall, who contrary to Declarations, Acts of Parliament, and Engagements, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> sealed with so much bloud, and without the appointment of God or his people, hath usurpt the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Office of chief Magistrate over the Nation, broken down the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of right and freedome, so lately cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for, with a vast expence of bloud and treasure, trampled upon that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest spirit in them turned out of the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Parliament, who were going on in the work and cause of God, casting some of them into prison upon that very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and doth exercise the same and worse Tyranny and Oppression in the very forme and method the King went in; opposing the work and cause of God in this day, and acting as upon the foundation so from a tincture, of the spirit, of the beast, and Antichrist: Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se things considered, why may we
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115117:16"/> not as honestly not onely pray, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour all we can, that he may be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed after the examrle of former Tyrants and Ʋsurpers, and rejoyce to see the judgments written against such wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, executed upon him, who hath so caused the honour of Christ to suffer by his Apostacy, and building again the things that were once destroyed; &amp; if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your extracting the very spirit of these Scriptures, you declare that <hi>Saul</hi> who was annointed by God to be King, might be opposed; then by the same ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument your Protector and unlawfull power may be opposed much more. And therefore in vain do you and others urge the <hi>13. Rom.</hi> and other Scriptures against those w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o oppose your Generall, as resisters of Magistracy; for he hath no more right to the power he hath, than a Thief to that purse which he hath taken from another on the high-way, for he is neither called of God, chosen by the people, nor hath he gained it by Conquest, one of which ingredients must needs be in his exaltation, if ye will convince us he is a lawfull power.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 11. They desire the costly pomp in the Court may be sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended for a good number of years, and that Revenue to be disposed towards publick charges, debts and damages for the easing of the people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And do also desire a period to be put to that Parliament, and that care be taken for future equal elections, and that none should e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or be elected, that were enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the late war against the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, nor any other who op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose that settlement promised, and that the future power in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments might be cleared, as supream onely, and that no foundations of common right might be given away, <hi>&amp;c-</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that no King be hereafter admitted but upon election of, and as upon trust from the people, by such their Representatives, not without fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st disclaming all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to a negative voice, against the determination of the Cōmons in Parliament, and this to be done in some forme more clear than he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etofore in the Coronation O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th.</p>
               <p>We propound these matters of General settlement to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> provided by the Authority of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Commons in that Parliament, &amp; be to further established by a generall contract, or agreement of the people with
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115117:17"/> their subscriptions thereto, &amp; that no King be admitted to the Crown, nor other person to any office of publique trust without expresse ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and subscription to the same.</p>
               <p>For our parts let but that way of justice be effectually prosecuted, and the settlement of the publique Interest be assured to us, and the Nation, we shall desire discharge from our present service, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:115117:17"/>
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>Do not these d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sires of yours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne your present practice, who now main<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ain your Generall in his wastefull spending a great part of the publick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, to uphold the pride, pomp and luxury of his Court.</p>
                  <p>But contrary to the very spirit of this your Generall in usurping the power into his own hand, doth not onely op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose this settlement, but robs the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Trustees of that supream power which only and of right belongs to them, and will let none be chosen nor sit, but such as own and acknowledge his power by indenting they will not alter it, as in <hi>Instr. Gov.</hi> Article <hi>34.</hi> neither will he let any thing passe that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on in his Parliament, for the good of the Nation if it clash therewith, as it appeares A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ticle of the <hi>lostr. 24.</hi> which is grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er slavery than when we were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the King, and for you or any other to consent hereto, is to give away th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of common right and freedome, which you seemed so much to contend for.</p>
                  <p>Your Protecto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> contrary to this hath forced himsel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and government upon the people, without the accord, subscription, or election of themselves, or Represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and hath usurped to him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elfe a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative voice, and thereby doth con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict what ever is done by his pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ended Parliament if it comply not with his Inte est.</p>
                  <p>Your profession is fair, why do you not then make use of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> swords to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme your wordes, but unworthily suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer your fellow Souldiers, and others, the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hfull Patriots, and assertors of the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tions interest to be persecuted and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115117:17"/> imprisoned for pressing after the publi{que} good, according to the true intent and spirit of your desires made known here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Is it not rather your duty now to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate to your Protector, as then you did to the Parliament, &amp; say as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did in <hi>Jonath.</hi> case to <hi>Saul 1 Sam. 14.4, 5.</hi> shall our brethren who with us have wrought so great salvation in <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> be thus persecuted, imprisoned, and unworthily dealt withall; and so res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue your brethren from the hand of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:115117:17"/>
               <head>In the Petition annexed to the Agreement of the people, presented to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of England in Parliament, on Satturday <hi>January 20. 1648.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>We hold our selves obliged to give the people all assurance possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that our opposing the corrupt closure endeavoured with the King was not in design, to hinder peace and settlement, (thereby to render our employments as Soldiers neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to be continued) and that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that extraordinary course we have taken, nor any other proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ours, have been intended for the setting up of any particular party, or Interest, by or with which to uphold our selves, in power and dominion over the Nation, but that it was, and is the desire of our hearts in all we have done (with the hindering of that eminent evill and destructive conjunction with the King) to make way for the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of the peace and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdome upon
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115117:18"/> grounds of common freedome and safety: And be cause our former overtures to that purpose (being in only general termes, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to a certainty of perticulars fit for practice) might possibly be understood, but as plausible preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, not intended really to be put into effect; we have thought it our duty to draw out those generalls into an entire forme of particulars ascertained with such circumstance, as may make it effectively practicable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We are far from such a spirit, as possitively to impose our private apprehensions, upon the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of any in the kingdome that have not forfeited their freedome, and much lesse upon your selves, neither are we apt in any wise, to insist upon circumstantiall things, or ought that is not evidently fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall to that publique interest, for which you and we have declared and engaged: But in this tender of it we humbly desire.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That whether it shall be fully approved by you, and received by the people (as it now stands) or not, it may yet remain upon Record before you, a perpetuall Witnesse of our reall intentions, and utmost endeavours, for a sound and equall settlement, and as a Testimony whereby all men may be assu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, what we are willing and ready to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiesse in, and their jealousies satisfied, or their mouthes stopt, who are apt to think, or say, we have no bottome:</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>You say your hindering that corrupt closure with the King, and all your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary courses and proceedings therein, was onely to make way, that the peace and Government of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, might be settled upon grounds of publique freedome and safety, and not setting up of any particular party or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, to uphold your selves in power and dominion over the Nation. And this you declare as a perpetuall witnesse of your reall intentions, to bottom in that sound and equal way of settlement, by the peoples Representors, freely and successively chosen into the supream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, without a single person and his Councill, by a Negative voice, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule them, or to pick and cull them for his interest; this comes freely from your selves, for your own vindication, to stop the mouthes, and satisfie the jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115117:18"/> of those, who it seems then fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red what now is come upon them: But do you not contrary to all this, maintain and uphold your Protector and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill, a private and particular interest, who have Arbitrarily usurped to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, power and dominion over the Nation, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reby rooting up that very foundation of common right and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, placed in the peoples Represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, ye so much declared you would bottome in; so that they cannot be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen by them, much lesse sit with free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and safety, except they first sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to his Government, which if they should do, they not onely strengthen him in his usurpation, but do betray and give a way the just Rig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts and Liberties of the people, into his hands, after our great contending for them, with so vast an expence of bloud and treasure.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <head>Here followes the Agreement of the People.</head>
               <p>Page 7. God having so far owned our Cause, as to deliver the enemies therof into our hands, we do now hold our selves bound in mutuall duty to each other, to take the best care we can for the future, to avoid both the danger of returning into
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115117:18"/> a slavish condition, and the charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able remedy of another war. For as it cannot be imagined, that so many of our Countrey men would have opposed us in this quarrell, if they had understood their own good, so may we hopefully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise to our selves, that when our common right and priviledges shall be cleared, their endeavours will be disappointed, that seek to make themselves our Masters; since therefore our former oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, and not yet ended troubles, have been occasioned, either by want of frequent Nationall meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in Councill, or by the undue or unequall constitution thereof, or by rendring those meetings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectuall. We are fully agreed and resolved (God willing) to provide that hereafter that our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentatives be neither left to an uncertainty for time, nor be une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually constituted, nor made use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, to the ends for which they are appointed, <hi>&amp;c. And so they go on, presenting what they had agreed upon under ten generall Heads, whereof onely some of the greater conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nment (for brevity sake) are here mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>You having at that time a potent Enemy to deal withall, your care was good to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> use of your power, for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of future slavery, and embroil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of another war: But now the case is otherwise; this potent Enemy being
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115117:18"/> vanquished, there is none but your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, who doth oppose the settling of us in our rights and liberties, against whom there needs not the like force and power, having no party to strengthen his hands but your selves, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you withdraw your assistance from him (who seeks to make himself our master as well as yours) there can be no fear of another war; but if you still adhere to uphold his usurped inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, who hath no more right to the power he hath than any of you; and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this accompt another warr ensue, your selves are guilty of all the bloud that shall be spilt, which we hope you will not do, if you so well understood your good, as you pretended to do when you spake these words; for as you did then, so we do now reckon it our duty, to endeavour that the Representors of the people, who have not forfeited their liberty, should not onely meet, but be preserved from the power of any that would endeavour to hinder them in their Counsells and actings for the glory of God and the publique good, and it is your duty according to these your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions, to be assisting to us therein, that so our fears and jealousies may be removed, otherwise we shall have ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t cause to conclude, that your intentions were indeed to hold up your selves in power, and to Lord it over the people by the sword, notwithstanding all your fair pretences in your overtures, and expressions mentioned in this Agreement.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>First, that to prevent the many inconveniences apparently arising from the large continuance of the same persons in supream Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, this present Parliament end, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115117:19"/> dissolve, upon, or before the last day of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1649.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>And is it not much more inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and dangerous, that your Protector, who was chosen neither by God nor his people, should impose his Government u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115117:19"/> us during life, with a provision for his successors to do the same.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>Thirdly, that the people do of course choose themselves a Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentative once in two years, &amp; shall meet for that purpose upon the first Thursday in every second <hi>May, &amp;c.</hi> And the Representative so chosen to meet the second Thursday in <hi>June</hi> following, at the usuall place in <hi>Westminster,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, that each Representative shall within twenty dayes after their first meeting, appoint a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill of State, for the managing pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Affairs, untill the tenth day after the meeting of the next Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentative, unlesse that next Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentative think fit to put an end to that Trust sooner, and the same Councill to Act, and proceed therein according to such instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and limitations, as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentative shall give and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, that in each intervall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Bienniall Representatives the Councill of State (in case of immen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt danger, or extreme necessity) may sommons a Representative to be forth with chosen, and to meet so, as the session thereof continue not above fourscore dayes, and so as it dissolve at least fifty dayes before the appointed time for the next Bienniall Representative, and upon the 50th. day so proceeding it shall dissolve, of course, if not otherwise dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved sooner.</p>
               <p>Eightly, that the Representative have, and shall be understood to have the supream Trust, in order to the preservation and governm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt of the whole, and that their power extend without the consent or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of any other person, or persons, to the erecting and abolishing of Courts of Justice and publique Offices, and to the enacting, repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and declaring of Laws, and the highest, and finall Judgement,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115117:19"/> concerning all naturall and civill things, but not concerning things spirituall and Evangelical, provided that even in things naturall and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, these six particulars next following are, and shall be understood to be excepted and reserved for our Representatives. <hi>Four whereof are onely m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntioned.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>By these following particulars you do acknowledge, that all just power is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally and essentially in the people, and that their free choice or consent by their Representors, is the on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall and foundation of all ju t Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, so that Rulers proceed from them, &amp; not they from their Rulers; as also that its very unsafe and dangerous, that this power of managing publique affairs, should be in the hands of any, but such as they entrust. Yet how contrary here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto your actings are let all men judge; For hath not your Protector and his creatures, or rather his creators, some of your chief Officers with others of his Councill (so called) assumed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves the supream Trust, in order to the preservation and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>overnment of the people, and improving the Militia, w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> should be for the peoples defence, not to the quelling of their Enemies, but the faithfull Assertors and Keepers of their Liberties, and nothing can be done, but what subjects to their restrictions.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>First, we do not impower them to imprest or constrain any person to serve in forreign war, either by Sea or Land, nor for any Military service within the Kingdome, save that they may take order for the Training and exercising the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in a Military way, to be in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diness for resisting forreign invasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, suppressing of suddain or for assisting in execution of Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, That in any Laws hereafter to be made, no person by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of any Tenure, Grant, Charter Patent, degree of Birth, shall be privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged from subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction thereto, or from being bound thereby, as well as others.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>Yet you do that your selves, or suffer your Protector in doing of it, which you would not allow to the supream Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Nation, witnesse the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse expedition both to the <hi>Streights, Hispaniola,</hi> and <hi>Jamica,</hi> which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant practice is by the Law of God counted man-stealing, and punishahle with death, <hi>Exod. 21.15.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>Fifthly, That the Representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive may not give judgment upon any mans person or estate where no Law hath before provided, save on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in calling to accompt, and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing pub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ique Officers, for abusing or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayling th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir trust.</p>
               <p>Six<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hly, That no Representative may in any wise render up, or give, or take away any foundations of common right and safety conteyned in this agreement, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <p>And if it was an evill to passe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon any without Law, much more to imprison the faithfull Patriots of the Country against Law, and never bring them to a due tryall.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>Tenthly, It is agreed that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever shall by force of Armes resist the Orders of the next or any fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Representative (except in case where such Representative shal evidently render up, or give, or take away the foundations of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon right, liberty and safety con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in this Agreement) shall forth with after his or their such re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115117:20"/> loose the benefit and protection of the Lawes, and shall be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished with death as an Enemy and Traytor to the Nation. All these we do accompt, and declare to be fundamental to our common Right, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Safety, and therefore do both agree thereunto, and resolve to maintain the same as God shall enable us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <p>And if unlawfull in the peoples Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentors to take, or give away any of these foundations of right and freedome, and may be opposed upon that accompt, than much more may your Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rals up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>start power which hath raised it selfe out of the ruines of the peoples liberties, and is rather the excressence than any part of the essence of a Lawfull pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115117:20"/>
               <head>And in the Declaration annexed to this Agreement coming after</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 7. To the end that mens jealousies and fears may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, concerning any intentions in us to ho d up our se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ves in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to oppresse or domineere over the people by the sword, and that all men may understand those grounds of peace, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, whereupon they may rest assured, we shall for our parts acqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sse; we have spent much time to prepare, and have at last (thorough the blessing of God) finisht a draught of such settlement, in the nature of an Agreement of he people for a peace amongst themselves, which we have lately presented to the Honourable the Commons assembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and do herewith tender to the people of this Nation; which contains the best and most hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full foundations for the future peace, and well government of the Nation, that we can devise or think on, within the line of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane power, and such wherein all the people intrested in this land, that have not particular interests of advantage, and power over o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, devided from that which is common and publick, are indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently &amp; equally provided for, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:115117:20"/>
               <p>But if God shall (in his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous judgement towards this land) suffer the people to be so blinded, as not to see their own common good and freedome, endeavoured to be provided for therein; or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to be so deluded (to their own and publique prejudice) as to make opposi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion thereto, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct of it be hindered, we have yet by the preparation and tender of it, discharged our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences to God, and duty to our Native Countrey, in our utmost endeavours for a settlement (to the best of our understandings) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a just publique interest, and hope we shall be acquitted before God, and good men, of any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trouble, distractions, or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series to the Kingdome, which may arise thorough the neglect, and rejection thereof, or opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereto, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 29. We (for our parts) are far from any desire or thought, to assume or exercise a law-giving, or judiciall power over the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or to meddle in any thing, save the fundamentall settling of that power, in the most equall and hopefull way for common right, freedome and safety, as in this Agreement, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>And if to take the power out of the hands of a singl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> person and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill, who did (and naturally do) make use thereof to their own particular and private interests, and placing it in the hands of the peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Repr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntors, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and successiv ly chosen, was the most hopefull and b st foundation, that within the line of humane power could be devised, or thought on for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture well government, and peace of the Nation, and that which provided for all who minded publique good, and had not particular interests and desire of ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vantage to themselves, and of pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r over others; and so much good laid up herein, as it had been a Judgement from the Lord upon the Nation, to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the people to be so farr blinded, and deluded, to their own and publique prejudice, to put off, oppose, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, this good and freedome coming to them, in this safe and settled way to publique interest: And your ednea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours after, and propounding this way of se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, such a discharge of your Conscience and duty to God, and your Countrey, and that which would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit you before him and good men, from blame of any futher trouble, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the Nation, which might arise in reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and opposing of it. And that you
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115117:20"/> had not a thought or desire, to assume or exercise, a law-giving, or judiciall power over the Nation, and would meddle no further, than to see it set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled in the peoples Representors, as the most hopefull way for the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of common right and freedome. Then what is the reason, you have now so soon altered if not your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be sure your practice, in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding your Generall, who hath made hims lf Chief Magistrate, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hath usurped this power out of that way, wherein you acknowledged it most safe, placing it in himself, and Councill, as it was in the King, when you thus complained against it? Now if from a tincture of that spirit that ranne in the King and his party, which you have received from their Houses, Parks, and Revenves <hi>(Deut. 7.26.)</hi> you are thus turned about to build upon their foundation, and to walk in those wayes of Tyranny, to the hind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring publique w lfare, you so condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in them; Then assure your selves, if you persist herein, there are a Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant whom the Lord keeps fai hfull to the true interest of Christ, and the Nation, who being more refined in that spirit, and those principles you here seem to be acted by, that by his assistance, do all you can to hinder them, will never give him nor you re t, till they see this foundation of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny you have l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ely mounted upon, and the things you have built thereon, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed; and the liberties you seemed to contend so highly for, secured in the best and safest way, and most agreeable to the true intent and spirit of your Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strances, Engagements, and Declarations, so farre as they accord with the Scriptures.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:115117:21"/>
               <head>From the Agents of Lievt. Generalls Regiment, Commissary Generalls Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Collonel <hi>Fleetwoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>'s Regiment, Collonel <hi>Whaley</hi>'s Regiment, Collonel <hi>Rich</hi> his Regiment.</head>
               <head type="sub">For the Noble and highly Honoured, the Free borne people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in their rtspective Counties and divisions these.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Countrimen and fellow Commoners.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>For your sakes, our friends, estates and lives have not been dear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, for your safety and freedome we have chearfully endured hard labours, and run most desperate hazards, and in comparison to your peace and freedom, we neither do, nor ever shall value our dearest blood, and we professe our bowels are, and have been troubled, and our hearts pained within us, in s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing, and considering that you have b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en so long bereaved of these fruits and ends of all our labours and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rds. We cannot but sympathize with y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u in your miseries, and Oppressions; its grief and vex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion of heart to us, to receive your meat, and monyes, whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st you have no advantage, nor yet the foundations of your peace and freedome, surely laid.</p>
               <p>And therefore upon most serious consideration, that your principle Right, most essentiall to your well being, is the clearn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, suffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iency, and freedome of your power, in your Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentatives in Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And minding, that for this Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ht of ours, and yours: we engaged our lives: For the King raised the warr against you, and your Parliament, upon this ground, that he would not suffer your Representatives to proceed or your peace, safety and freedome, that were then in danger by dispencing the Militia; and otherwise according to their trust, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and defence of that power and right of yours, we hazzarded all that was dear to us; and God hath been witnesse to the justice of our Cause. And further, minding that the onely effectuall means, to settle a just and lasting Peace, to obtain remedy for all your grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and to prevent future Oppressions, is; the making clear and secure the power that you betrust to your Representatives in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. Upon all these grounds, we propound your joyning with us in the Agreement herewith sent unto you, that by vertue thereof, we may have Parliaments certainly called, and have the time of their sitting and ending certain; and their power and trust, clear and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stionable; that after they may remove your burthens, &amp;c. That there may be no grounds for future quarrells or contentions, to oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115117:21"/> warr or bloodshed, and we desire you would consider, that as these things wherein we offer to agree with you, are the fruits and ends of the victories which God hath given us, so the settlement of these are the most absolute means to preserve you, and your posterity, from sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, oppression, distraction and trouble. By this those whom your selves shall choose, shall have power to restore you to, and secure you in all your rights, and they sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l be in a capacity to taste of Subjection as well as Rule, and so shall be equally concerned with your selves, in all they do, for they must equally suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r with you under any common bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and partake with you in any freedomes, and by this they shall be disi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abled to defraud or wrong you, when the Laws shall bind all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out priviledge, or exemption; and by this your consciences sha l be free from Tyranny and oppression, and those occasions of endless strifes and bloody warrs sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l be perfectly removed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if any shall enquire why we undertake to offer this Agreement, we must pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>esse we are sensible that you have been so often deceived with Declarations and Remonstrances, and fed with vain hopes, that you have reason to abandon all confidence in any persons whatsoever, from whom you have no other security of their intending your free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome then bare D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>larations: And t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erefore as our Consciences wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness that in simplicity, and integrity of heart, we have proposed lately in the <hi>Case of the Army stated</hi> your freedome, and deliverance from slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Oppression, and all burdens, so we desire to give you satisfying as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance thereof by this Agreement, whereby the found tions of your freedome provided in <hi>the Case, &amp;c.</hi> shall be settled unalterably, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Agents coming from other Regiments unto us have subscrib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Agreement, to be propos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to their respective Regiments and yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>And doth not your Protector in this day bere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve us of the very same foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of Right and fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>edome, which we hoped to receive as the fruit o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Why then are you not grieved, &amp; why do you not stand up with the like Resolution and Courage now as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n? And if you hazarded all that was near and dear unto you in opposing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> King, because he bounded the peoples Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentors, and would not suffer them to dispose the Militia according to their Trust, for the safety of the Nation. And if t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Lord hath borne witnesse to the justice of your Consein so doing, ought you not then in this day to stand up upon the same grounds ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inst your Protector who hath assumed the whole power of the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tia (as the King then endeavoured to do) and thereby hath wrested the power and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115117:22"/> trust thereof out of our Representors hands, which of right belongs to them. And will not the Lord (think you) own you in opposing him, as formerly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the King: And if you thought in that day that the onely effect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uall meanes to settle a just and lasting peace, and to prevent future Oppression, Warr, and bloud-shed, was to secure and clear the power betrusted with such Representors distinct from a single person, and his Councill; and this of so high concernment, that you judged it Necessary to stirr up the people by this Agreement to assist you therein. Is there not then upon the same grounds, and for the same ends, cause for us to minde you of these things, and to call upon you at this day to do your duty, to helpe pull down the like usurped power now in a Protector, which you then opposed in the King; and which he is not able to uphold without you? For if you unanimously declare your selves for the good of your Countrey, against these Innovators; you may in the mean time, till the peoples Representors, who have not forfeited their liberty, can meet and settle things upon their due Basis, put a stop upon all the publique Revenues, which these men have diverted out of the right channell, to themselves; em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering such as are confiding men with Receipt thereof, in d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing whereof you shall by the Lords assistance, recover our lost liberties without expence of Treasure, or shedding of bloud▪ For it is well known that your Protector and his Courtiers, are not so well beloved, either at home or abroad, as to raise a considerable force in opposition to you, and the Countrey herein. And further to move you hereunto, consider the deplorable estate of our Nation, and let your Bowells yearn towards us your fellow Commoners, who are not onely made Vassalls as to our persons and liberties, but our estates wasted, our publique Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures exhausted, many of our ships decayed and lost, and thousands of our men slain and perished in a sinfull and fruitlesse expedition to <hi>Hispaniola:</hi> Whereby through the righteous judgement of God, our Nation, which was formerly a terrour to all the Nations round about, is now become a scorn: So tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> we have not onely lost our liberties and estates, but God, his Name, and Glory also. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l which considered, we doubt not but you will have such a deep sense upon your spirits, of the dishonour brought upon the Cause of God, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable ruine which hangeth over the Nation (if God prevent not) as will awaken you, and stir up your former Zeal for God and your Countrey But if after all this you shall fit still, and neglect to do your Duty: then know it for a tru h, that the Lord will raise up Deliverance some other way, and that speedily; and you and your house shall perish, as <hi>Mordecay</hi> said to <hi>Esther, Esther 4 14.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115117:22"/>
               <head>Four Acts of Parlament past after the Death of the late King.</head>
               <head type="sub">First that of <hi>January 30. 1648.</hi> the same day, or the day after the late King was Beheaded.</head>
               <p>VVHereas <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> being for the notorious Treasons, Tyrannies, and Murders commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him in the late unnaturall and cruell Warrs condemned to Death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Be it enacted and ordained by this present Parliament, and by the Authority of the same, that no person, or persons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, do presume to Proclaim, Declare, Publish, or any way pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> Sonne of the said <hi>Charles,</hi> commonly called the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> or any other person, to be King or Chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, of <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> or of any the Dominions belonging to them, or either of them, by colour of Inheritance, Succession, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, or of any other Claims whatsoever; without the free con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the people in Parliament; first had, and signified, by a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Act or Ordinance, for that purpose, any Statute, Law, U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage, or Custome to the contrary hereof in any wise notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. And be it further Enacted and Ordained, that whosoever shall contrary to this Act Proclaim, Declare, Publish, or any way pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the said <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> the Sonne, or any other person to be King, or Chief M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gistrate of <hi>England,</hi> or of <hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> without the said consent in Parliament si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nified as aforesaid, shall be deemed, and judged a Traitor to the Commonwealth, and shall suffer pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of death, and such other punishments as belong to the Crimes of high Treason: And all Officers, aswell Civill as Military, and all other well aff cted persons, are hereby Authorised and required, forthwith to apprehend all such Off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nders, and to bring them in safe cust<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dy to the next Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of peace, that they may be proceeded against accordingly.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>Then by this and the other following Acts not yet repealed by Parliamen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that was like a Parliament, being also b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>und by his own and his Creatures <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>str.</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> Article <hi>6.</hi> which saies, that no Law shall be alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, suspended, abrogated, or repealed, or new Laws made, nor any Taxe, Charge, or imposition laid upon the people, but by common consent in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. Your Protector having usurpt the power of Chief Magistracy over the Nation, without the Consent of the peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Representors, who are the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Authority, is a Triator; and so were all those who were ayders of Abet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ors,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115117:23"/> to and Proclaimors of him: And do deserve death, and the other punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as belong to the Crime of high Treason: And it is as lawfull for any well-affected person, or Officr to apprehend him and his Abettors, to bring them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e next Justice of the peace, to be proceeded against accordingly, as to have apprehended <hi>Charles Stu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rt</hi> or any other person who would have proclia'md him King or chief Magistrate in that day.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <p>The Second Acte past <hi>March</hi> 17. 1648. entituled <hi>An Act for the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing the Kingly Office in</hi> England.</p>
               <p>Whereas <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> late King of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by declared to be justly condemned and put to death <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for many Treasons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereby his posterity, and all others pretending Title under him, are become uncapable of the said Crowns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or to have the Name, Title, Stile or Dignity of King, <hi>&amp;c</hi> or to have the Power or Dominion of the s id Kingdomes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or the Honours, Mannors, Lands, Tenements, Possessions and Heriditaments, belonging or apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taning to the said Crown of <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi> And whereas it is, and hath been found by experience, that the Office of a King in this Nation and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to have the power thereof in any single person is unneces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, burthensom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and dangerous to the liberty, safety and publique inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st of the people, and that for the most part, use hath been made of the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gall power, and Prerogative, to oppress<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, impoverish, and insl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve the Subject. And that usually and naturally, any one person in such power makes it his interest, to encroach upon the just freedome and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the people, and to promote the setting up of their own will and power above the Laws, that so they might ensl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve the Kingdoms to their own lusts. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it therefore enacted and declared, by this present Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That the Office of a king in this Nation shall n t henceforth reside in, or be exercised by any one single person. And that no one person whatsoever, shall or may hold the Office, Stile, Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Power or Authority of a King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if any person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons shall by force of Armes or otherwise, be ayding, and assisting to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny persons, that sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll by any way and means, be promoting any to that Office, (or to that purp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se) That then every such offence shall be de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and adjudged high Treason, <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>And may not the Free-born people of the Nation, who have had such renewed and wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ull experience, by the evill carriage and practises of your Protector since he usurped the power of chief Magistrate over them, tending chiefly for the advance of his Interest: Say upon good grounds, that it is indeed unnecessary, burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115117:23"/> and dangerous to the liberty, safety, and publique interest of the people, to have such a power in the hands of a single person. For is it not as evident as she Sun in the firmament, that as his Predecessors formerly did, so he doth oppresse, impoverish, and enslave the Nation to his lusts, in setting up his Arbitrary will and power, contrary to, and above the Law, as may appear by severall instances, if there were roome to mention them: Wherefore have we not good reason to abominate and oppose this power as in him, so also in the hands of any other person whatsoever, though never so Godly; and to be confided in, till our Lord Jesus Christ doth come whose right it is?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>The Third Act of Parliament past 14. <hi>May</hi> 1649. which in a manner is all one with the Fourth; and therefore not Transcribed.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Fourth Act of Parliament past</hi> July 17. 1649.</head>
               <p>Whereas the Parliament hath abolished the kingly Office in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> And having Resolved, and Declared, that the people for the future, shall be Governed by its own Representatives, and Nationall meetings in Councill, chosen and entrusted by them. For that purpose hath settled the Government in a Common-weal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h and Free-State without a King, and House of Lords: Be it Enacted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That if any person shall malitiously, or advisedly publish by writing, printing, or open declaring, That the said Government is Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall, Usurped, or Unlawfull; And that the Commons ass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbled in Parliament, are not the Supream Authority of this Nation, or shall Plot, Contrive, or endeavour to stir up and raise force, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That then every such offence shall be taken, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emed, and adjudged by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of this Parliament, to be High Treason.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>The Generallity of Well-affected people in the Nation, who went along in the Work and Cause of God in that day with you, approved of, and consented to these four Acts and Engagement, which contein in them a full provision, for the keeping out of Monarchy, and the p wer from being in the hands of a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle person and his Councill; which they saw (as by their experience in the late King and his Family) would unavoidably stifle in the very birth, their and your desires, made known in your severall Remonstrances, Declarations, and Engagements (for the well-being, freedome, and safety of the people) which have since been sealed with so much of the Saints and others bloud. But after all this, your Protector to satisfie his desire of Domination, and the better to keep down that honest spirit (in those Members who were turned out
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115117:24"/> of the Little Parliament) from going on in the work of Christ, and would not submit to mans interest, hath by his Arbitrary power and force, Contrary to these Acts and Engagements, and other Laws of the Land, and the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and spirit of Remonstrances, and Declarations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And without the desires, approbation, and Consent of the well affected of the Nation, broken down, and trampled upon the Supream Authority the peoples Represent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs, and usurpt their power and Trust into his own hand, and having thus exalted himself on the ruines of the Nations rights and freedome, he is become guilty of High Treason; And for lesse than this, <hi>Strafford</hi> and <hi>Canterbury</hi> lost their Heads.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>
                  <hi>And as by these Acts, so also be an Engagement drawn up and sent out by that Parliament about that time, for all in the Nation (who were concerned) to signe, which runs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I do hereby declare and promise to be true and faithfull to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>England,</hi> as now establish without a King and house of Lords.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>Your Protector being then Lievtenant Generall, and the Army stood by up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Parliament in the foregoing Acts and this Engagement, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded strongly that such as refused to signe it might suffer, and many Ministers with others, suffered in their estates and otherwise, for not signing of it: Besides this it was sent to the severall Regiments both of horse and foot in the Army to be signed and sealed, and was done accordingly, as a publique Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and Declaration they intended not to set up themselves in the same things, they had so condemned and cast out in e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hers.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <head>In a Declaration of the English Army upon their March into <hi>Scotland 19. July 1650.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 5. We were engaged in a Warr with the late King for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our Religion and Liberties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nothing l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sse would satisfie him, than to have it in his own power, to destroy Religion, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, the subversion whereof he had often attempted; that he was a man guilty of more innocent bloud in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (even of those he ought to have preserved as a Father his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren) than any of his Predecessors, or we think than any History mentioneth, the guilt whereof he brought upon his Family, by so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne appeales to God: That the Sonne did tread in the Fathers st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ps and pursue his designes, destructive to Religion and Liberty: That
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115117:24"/> a party in Parliament, false to God &amp; their trust, were willing, &amp; did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, to betray the Cause into the late Kings hands. That a remaining Party desiring to be true to God and to the people that entrusted them, out of integrity of heart, and fearing that the high displeasure of God would fall upon them if they had not done it, did bring to justice, and cause to be executed the said King; did reject the person now with you; did lay aside the House of Lords (an Estate not represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the people, nor trusted with their Liberties, yet at that time ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry forward to give up the peoples Rights, and obstruct what might save them, and alwayes apt enough to joyn with Kingly interest, against the peoples Liberties, whereof we wish you have not like sad experience) and did for the good of the people, Resolve the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into a Common-wealth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 9. We reckon it no Breach, but a Religious keeping of the Covenant according to the equity thereof, when our Parliament for Religion and Liberties sake, and the interest of the people, did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the King and Kingship.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>And hath not your Generall assumed the very same and greater power to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, to the subversion of the peoples Liberties, which the King in his often attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pting to uphold himself in, shed so much innocent bloud in that day. And if that party in the Old Parliament, who would have closed with the Kings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest against the peoples Liberties, were false to God, his Cause, and the Trust committed to them; then they of the Little Parliament were so, who left their fellow-Members in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> House, and ranne away with their pretended power to your Generall, and so will all those be that hereafter shall approve of, and confirme his Ʋsurpation. And if they were true to God, and their Trust, who opposed the King in his Tyranny, and brought him to justice; and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to provide against such Oppression and slavery for the future; then they who were turned out of the Little Parliament, were so; for they were pressing on with more refinednesse upon the same account; and so will all others be faithfull to the Lord, who upon right and spirituall principles shall op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> Tyranny, and are true friends and assertors of all just Liberty. And if the Kingly interest and Kingship was so opposite and destructive to the peoples Libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties then, and changing the Government from Kingly into a Common-wealth so much for their good; it is so now:</p>
                  <p>Hitherto you Declare and Act like the best common wealths men, and as the greatest opposers of Monarchy and haters of Tyranny; and the onely faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full friends and Assertors of publique Liberty; and in the Declaration and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115117:25"/> Speech comming after, you seem to forget the things behind, and to be pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing towards the advancement of Christs Kingdome, and to lay him as a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, not onely to Rule in our hearts; but as to the Rule and Government of the world: But comparing these high expressions with your present actions, you are so far from pressing after the Kingdome of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, that ye are not so much as good Common-wealths men; but rather like <hi>Demus,</hi> for the muck of this world and the favour of men, have forsaken these good old principles wherein the Lord so owned you, and are set down with your Protectors inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, and do uphold the same Monarchy, Tyranny and Oppression in him, which was opposed in the King with so vast an expence of bloud and treasure, to the dishonour of God and grief of his people.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="declaration">
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="declaration">
                           <head>In a Declaration of the Officers, and Souldiers of the <hi>English</hi> Army in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Anno <hi>1650.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>At the beginning of the great, and wonderfull workings of God, in these Nations of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> We the under Officers, and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of the <hi>English</hi> Army now in <hi>Scotland,</hi> were most of us if not all, men of private callings, &amp; not at all interested in matters of Publi{que} and State affairs, but yet very many of us, in whom the Lord had begun to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal himselfe in the face of Jesus Christ, were sensible of the Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Tyranny that was exercised by the late King, and his Prelates, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Consciences, bodies and estates of the true Spiritual Church of Jesus Christ, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Under these sad sufferings our Souls mourned, and understanding by the manifold gracious promises in the word of God, that a time of deliverance was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>xp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>cted to the Church of Christ, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>struction and ruine to Babylon; our hearts with all the truly godly in <hi>England,</hi> were exceedingly stirred up to pray to the Lord, even day and night, that he would arise to destroy Antichrist, and to save his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>et us remember how the Lord was pleased graciously to answer the prayers of his people at that time, in their deliverance from the Army raised by the late King and his prelates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> insomuch that soon after <hi>Scotland</hi> s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap> in peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>England</hi> obtains a Parliament, to whom they have opportunity to complain of their gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>vances, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the great goodnesse of God so constituted, that grievances are heard, and overtures made to the late King for their redresse, which was so irksome to his oppressive, Tyrannicall and bloody Spirit, that c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> gain betook himselfe to overthrow the Parliament by force, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                              <pb n="49" facs="tcp:115117:25"/> And with drawing himself from his Parliament, an appearance of a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill warr begins, which being made known to us the inferiour Officers &amp; Soldiers of this Army, (then in our private callings) we found our hearts extraordinarily stird up by the Lord to assist the Parliam<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. against the King, being abundantly satisfied in our judgements &amp; consciences, that we were called forth by the Lord, to be instrumentall to bring about that which was our continuall prayer to God, <hi>viz</hi> the destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Antichrist, and the deliverance of his Church and people. And upon this simple accompt we engaged, not knowing the deep policies of worldly States-men; and have ever since hazzarded our lives in the high places of the field (where we have seen the wonders of the Lord) against all the opposers of this wroke of Jesus Christ, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And having these things singly in our eye, namely the destruction of Antichrist, the advancement of the Kingdome of Jesus Christ, the deliverance, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of his Church in the establishment of his O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>dinances a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them in purity according to his word, and the just civill liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>English</hi> men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>We did many of us rejoyce at the Covenant because we found in it a strain towards these ends, although some being more enlightened, did apprehend it to be so mixt with worldly Intrests, that they justly fear'd the Interest of Jesus Christ would be only pretend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>d to, and the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ests of this world, yea, of Antichrist himself carried under a vizzard, as we have since had experience of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>We were then powerfully convinced that the Lords purpose was to deal with the late K. as a man of blood, &amp; being perswaded in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences that he &amp; his Monarchy was one of the 10. hornes of the Beast spoken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.12, 13, 14, 15. And being witnesses, to so much of the innocent blood of the Saints he had shed in supporting the Beast; &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the loud cries of the Souls of the Saints under the Alter, we were extraordinarily carried forth to desire justice upon the K. that man of blood. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>d to this purpose petitioned our Superiour Officers and the Parliament to bring him to justice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When God executes his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon malefactors let none go about to resist, when he brings forth these his enemies that will not suffer Jesus Christ in the midst of his Saints, and breaks them in pieces like a Potters v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ssell, let not <hi>Scotland</hi> nor any other Nation say what doest thou, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Lord that sees the secrets of all hearts, knowes the compliance of <hi>Scotland</hi> with the late Kings issue now with you, was in order to disturb the peace of <hi>England,</hi> for being Gods executioners upon a bloody Tyrant, and a supporter of the Throne of the Beast, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="50" facs="tcp:115117:26"/>
                           <p>But if there be any that have taken councell together against the Lord, and against his annointed whom the Lord hath decreed to set u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his holy hill of <hi>Syon,</hi> we are perswaded the Lord hath brought us hither as Instruments, thorough which he will speak to them in his wrath and vex them in his sore displeasure. We desire it may be known to you our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that we are not Souldiers of fortune, we are not merely the servants of men, we have not only proclaimed Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ the King of Saints, to be our King by profession; but desire to submit to him upon his own termes, and to admit him to the exercise of his Royall Authority in our hearts, and to follow him whereso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he goes, he having of his own good will entered into a Covenant of grace wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>h his poore Saints, and be assured it is he that leadeth us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Scotland,</hi> as he hath done in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and threfore we do in the Spirit of Brotherly love, and of the fear of the Lord beseech you to look about you, for our Lord Jesus is comming amongst you, us a refiners fire and sullers sope; and blessed are those in whom the least dram of sincerity shall be found. We have Paper directed to us from the people of <hi>Scotland,</hi> wherein we are first desired to consider the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of our marching into <hi>Scotland.</hi> We blesse God we did that before we came, and are abundantly satisfied that we are brought hither by the Lord, nay many of us lying under temptations of flesh &amp; blood, &amp; going about to frame excuses to take us from this march, found that to have stayed behind, had been to have turned our backs upon Jesus Christ and to have deprived our selves of much sweet Communion with God, that now thorough his goodnesse we do enjoy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>It is our prayer daily that those that fear the Lord, in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> may become one in the hand of the Lord, and joyn together in the advancement of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Kingdome of Jesus Christ, &amp; throwing down &amp; tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>mpling upon the seat of the Beast. Why should not <hi>Scotland</hi> as well as <hi>England</hi> rejoyce to see the horns of the Beast cut off, that we may joyn together to hate the Whore, and burn her flesh with fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We dare not any of us though tempted thereto by your Papers, be so car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally wise, as to desert the cause and worke of Jesus Christ, in which we have been hitherto so long and so miraculously carried on: Do you think we are men so weakly principled, as to be perswaded without the least strength of argument to desert the Interest of our own Nation, and expose thousands of the precious Saints of Jesus Christ to be trampled upon as dirt in the streets, when the Lord is about to put on their beautifull garments, and to make them a praise in the earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>And thus we have in the naked plainnesse of our Soules opened our hearts unto you our dear Brethren that fear the Lord in <hi>Scotland,</hi>
                              <pb n="51" facs="tcp:115117:26"/> where ever you be found, whether in the highest Councills or the meanest Cottages, who though you now be scattered the Lord in his due time will bring you together &amp; bind you up as his Jewells, &amp; make you one with those that fear the Lord among us; which the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, and in him our God and our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bring to passe in his due time, and in the mean time make you &amp; us wise to understand the things that concerne the exalting of Christs Kingdome, and that in all things we may be subservient to the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of Jesus Christ, and above all things take heed how we stir up any of the powers or strength of this world to destroy one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <dateline>
                                 <hi>From the Leagure at</hi> Musleborough <date>August 1. 1650.</date>
                              </dateline>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>If that the King and Bishops exercising their Tyrannicall will and power over the Consciences, bodies and estates of the people of God, contrary to Scripture and such Laws of the Land as are good, was a part of that Antichristian yoke which is promised shall wholy be destroyed, and for fulfilling whereof your hearts were so stirred up to pray unto him, and those prayers so graciously answered, in delivering the good people of <hi>Scotland</hi> from that Antichristian Army raised to force this Tyranny upon them; and in <hi>Englands</hi> obtaining a Parliament for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse of their grievances, and the Kings endeavouring by force to overthrow them instead of giving redresse therein, such an evidence of a tyrannnicall oppressing, and Antichristian spirit, which so stirred up your hearts to assist the Parliament against him: And your thus pleading for Liberty in opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Tyranny, an engaging in the work of Christ against Antichrist. And if upon this simple accompt you engaged and ventured your lives in the high places of the field, and had such a presence of the Lord with you against those opposers of the work of Jesus Christ; And were so powerfully convinced, that the King as a Monarch was one of the ten hornes of the Beast; and that the Lords purpose was to deal with him as a man of bloud, and as standing upon that foundation as followes in your Declaration: What letteth then but that such (who have the same Spirit for Christ against Antichrist, as here you do expresse) may upon the very same grounds forsake their Callings, and as one man joyn themselves together to assist the Lord Jesus against your Generall, who hath wrested (as we may say) out of the hands of Christ and his Saints, all the power and fruit of all our victories, bloud and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure expended against that bloudy Tyrant. Is not their Call as clear and just to assist Christ against <hi>Cromwell</hi> a very Jugler (to use his own words) as for you to assist the Parliament against <hi>Charles Stuart;</hi> doth not the Cry of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115117:27"/> your Bretherens Bloud from under the Alter, slain in opposing <hi>Charles,</hi> Cry as loud against <hi>Cromwell</hi> that hath actually bereaved us of our Liberties, as against <hi>Charles</hi> that would have d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne it? Besides the many thousands at <hi>Hispaniola, Jamica,</hi> and the Fleet, which have perished in a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous designe after the Spanish Treasure; and some faithfull servants of the Lord still kept in Prison against the Law of God, Nature, and Nations, for no other cause but pressing after the bringing forth these good things leading towards the advancement of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts Kingdome, and to what it shall be when the Law goes forth of Syon, <hi>Micha 4.2.</hi> which in these glorious words you seem so much to plead for; and for bearing their Testimony against your Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, who contrary to this and other Declarations is set down up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the Antichristian foundation of the late Monarch, which your selves confesse one of the ten Horns and a supporter of the seat of the Beast whose deadly wound he hath now healed; and do not wonder we say so, for it is not the most em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Saint in the world standing upon this foundation, that can excuse him from being a Horn of the Beat, or that from being the Beasts founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; neither can such a one (let him use his utmost endeavour) keep from shedding the bloud of the Saints, because as there is a natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all enmity planted by the Lord in their hearts against the Beast, from whence they can never let him be at rest, so this persecuting bloudy spirit is entayld and shall suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessively remain upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fourth Monarchy, till the Ancient of dayes sits, and the Saints poss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sse the Kingdome, <hi>Dan. 7.21, 22.</hi> When therefore the Lord shall execute judgement upon this grand Malefactor, let none go about to resist, for the Lord will if he repent not, bring him forth amongst other his enemies that will not suffer Jesus Christ to be King in the midst of his Saints, and break him in pieces like a Potters vessell; and let not <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> nor any other Nation, nor the Army say, what doest thou? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Lord that sees the secrets of all hearts, will shortly discover and unv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>il your Generalls secret desi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nes, so that it shall appear to all the world he is a self-seeker and a supporter of the seat of the Beast. And therefore such as together with him, shall take counsell against the Lord, and against his Anoynted whom he hath decreed to set upon his holy hill of Zyon, we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded the Lord will (as you said of your selves) bring his faithfull company together as instruments through whom he will speak to them in his wrath, and vex them in his sone displeasure: And be it know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to you Collonells, Commanders and others in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> that when such do come forth, they will not be Souldiers of fortune, nor in the least the servants of men; but of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, the King of Saints and Nations, who will then be declared to be their King; and will desire to submit to him upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s own terms, and to be ruled by his just and righteous
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115117:27"/> Laws: And therefore you are desired in the spirit of brotherly love and fear of the Lord to look about you, and take heed of siding with any interest a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst our Lord Jesus Christ, who as formerly to the Scots, is now comming amongst you as a Refiners fire and Fullers soape, to call you to an account and to redeem his blessed Cause and Interest, which you do d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>spise and cast out after your so highly declaring for it; and as you said to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m in that day, so may it be said to you, assure your selves that where the Lord finds most truth, sincerity and uprightnesse of heart, there he will be. And if when they are called to this work, they find flesh and bloud (as you did then) going about to frame excuses to take them off, and a desire rather to sit still because of the danger and difficulties that lies before them, and at the same time the Lord rousing up their spirits according to <hi>Numb. 23.24.</hi> in the sense of the disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour brought to his Name and Cause, and Conscience on the other hand check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and telling them this backwardness is to save their bodies and purses, and the Lord also withdrawing his presence upon the account of their backwardnesse, and if they find such workings as these in their hearts, may it not be as great a discovery that it is the will of the Lord, they should up and be doing, as it was to you when the same workings (as you here say) were upon your hearts, when called forth against the good people of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and if they decline herein when the Lord thus goes before them, do they not as much turn their backs upon Jesus Christ, as you should have done if you had declined going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Scotland</hi> in that day. It is our hearty desire and daily prayer, that all those who fear the Lord in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one in the hands of the Lord, and (for avoiding effusion of bloud) joyn together in advancing the Kingdome of Christ, and throwing down and tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling upon the seat of this Beast; and why should not you as well as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce to see the Horns of the Beast cut off? But if after this Brotherly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition you still resolve to uphold your Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rall in his Apostacy, and bloud be shed upon this account, then consider whether you do not shed the bloud of the Saints, in supporting the seat of the Beast, aswell as the King and his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers did, and thereby declare your selves (notwithstanding your high pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession for the Kingdome of Christ against th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Beast) to be acted by the spirit of those Captains and Mighty men <hi>Rev. 19.17, 18</hi> whose flesh is appointed to the fowles of the ayre, for their opposing of Jesus Christ and his followers.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <head>In a Declaration of the Army after the Old Parliament was dissolved, <hi>1653.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>We judged it necessary and agreed upon it, that the supream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority should be by Parliament divolved upon known persons, men
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115117:28"/> fearing God and of approved integrity and the Government com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittd to them for a time, as the most hopefull way to encourage and countenance all Gods people, reforme the Law, and administer justice impartially; hoping thereby the people might forget Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, and understanding their true interest in the Election of suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessive Parliaments, may have the Government settled upon a true Bassis without hazzard to this glorious Cause or necessitating to keep up Armes for the defence of the same, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>According to these desires and the great satisfaction of the publique-spirited people of the Nation, the supream Authority (though not by Parliament) was divolved into the hands of such persons (some of them at least) as here you mention, who were reforming the Law, administring justice impartially, and doing many other good things; and did so encourage and countenance the Lords people whilest th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, as they can tell you (and so will your selves say) that they and you never so rejoyced before nor since: And when they were ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly approving their hearts to the Lord herein, your Generall out of an itching desire of domination turns them out, assuming the Monarchicall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to himself; thereby reviving that ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ursed thing, it here pretended the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple should forget; diverting the fruit of all the bloud and treasure expended in this glorious Cause to his own lust; and hindering the faithfull people, who have not forfeited their liberty from settling the Government upon a true Bassis, to the great endangering another Warr.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <head>Here followes some Remarkable Passages in a Speech made by Generall <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> in his own name and the names of the Officers of the Army to the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Little Parliament, in the Councill Chamber, before their sitting; as much, or more worthy to be observed than any thing going before, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (among other things) a Declaration of the Armies principles, wound up to the height, as also of their proceedings, from the time they came from <hi>Worcester,</hi> till the Old Parliament was dissolved.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 1. 2. After divers turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of ass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yes, it pleased God much about the midst of this warr to winnow the forces of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to put them into the hands of men of other principles, than those that did engage at first <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Those strange windings and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115117:28"/> turnings of providence, those very great appearances of God in cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the designes of men, that he might raise up a contempa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ble com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of men not verst in Military affairs, nor having much naturall propensity to them through the owning a principle of godlines; which so soon as it came to be owned, and the State of affairs put upon that sort of account, how God blest them and all their undertakings you very wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> know, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 3 The issues of those suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses God was pleased to give to this Nation were very great things brought about, besides those dint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that were upon those Nations and places where they were carried on, even in the Civill affairs, to the bringing Offenders to justice; the state of of this Government to the name at least of a Common-wealth; the searching and sitting of all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and persons; the King remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and brought to Justice and many great on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with him; the House of Commons the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentative of the people of <hi>England</hi> winnowed, sifted, and brought to a handfull, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 4. As the effect of that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable Year 1648. was to lay the foundation of bringing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents to punishment, so it was of the change of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, although it be true the carriages of some in most eminent Trust was such as would have fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated to us the hopes of all our undertakings, by that closure that would have been endeavoured by the King, whereby we should have put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto his hands all that cause and interest we had opposed, and had nothing to have secured us but a little piece of paper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 5. When I and my fellow Officers and Souldiers came from
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115117:29"/>
                  <hi>Worcester,</hi> we expected having such a History to look back unto; a God that appeareth so eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, so visibly; the Mercies that God had shewed; the expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that were in the hearts of all good men, would have prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed those that were in Authority to have done those good things which might have been judged a return fit for such a God, and worthy of such Mercies, and a discharge of duty, to those for whom all these Mercies have been sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wed; that is, the true interest of the three Nations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 7. Upon our return we came fully bent in our hearts to desire and use all fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r &amp; lawfull means we could to have had the Nation reap the fruit of all that bloud and treasure that had been expended in this Cause, and had many thirstings in our spirits to find out waies and means <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o help it forward, and were very tender so much as to petition till <hi>August</hi> last, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <p>Hath the Lord begun thus in the Spirit? then surely he will not end in the flesh; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> so it would then become wisedome, if you would again expect the like appearances of God for you, and not be winnowed away as others, to keep close to, and be more refined in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se good old principles.</p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:115117:28"/>
                  <p>They were marvailous dispensations that made you so instrumental in those great revolutions, &amp; in winnowing the house til it became a handful, this hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full might be thought to be wheat, but did not your Gen. desire (as sometime the Devill did <hi>Peter</hi>) to winnow them all a way, not only the Chaff, but espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the good Wheat, that so he might get into the Saddle and play <hi>Rex</hi> alone, for he hath gotten into his hand all that Cause and Interest, that some in the House (you so complain of) would have given the King, and we have not so much as a piece of paper to secure us, the <hi>Instrument</hi> (as it is called) <hi>of Government,</hi> but indeed of Tyranny, is not the result of any Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulation between him &amp; the people his Superiors, but a manifestation of his Arbitrary will and power forced upon us without our consent: Surely the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of the Lord against this Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postacy will be greater (if he repent not) than the quashing those insur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> against his worke on foot in that day.</p>
                  <p>If you really minded the peoples good more than your own advancement
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115117:29"/> as is here pretended; as you would not have turned out those honest men of the little Parliament, when they were doing these good things: So surely you would have brought forth better fruit under your new Government (after almost three years growth) than yet you have, which is now little other then the building what had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed: Imprisoning the true Friends t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Cause of Christ, and the closing with corrupt interests as the King and Presbyterians did to hold up your self in power; which is very unsutable to all the bloud and treasure expended in this glorious Cause or that blessed spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit you here seem to be acted by.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 8. Finding the people dissatisfied in every corner of the Nation, and bringing home to our doors the non-performance of those thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gs that had been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised, we did think our selves concerned to keep up the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of honest men in the world, and therefore we had divers times endeavoured a Meeting with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Members of Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We had at the least ten or twelve Meetings beseeching them to do those things that had been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, that so it might appear they did not do th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m by any sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestion from the Army, but of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115117:29"/> their own ingenuities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring plainly that the issue would be the judgement of God against them, the dissatisfaction of the people, and the putting things into confusion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When we saw things would not be laid to heart, we considered amongst our selves what other way to have recourse unto, and when we came unto those close considerations, they began to take the Act of the New Representative to heart, and seemed excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding willing to put it on, the which had it been done, or would it have been done with that integrity, that would have saved this cause, and the interest we have been so long engaged in, there could nothing have happened to our judgements, more welcome than that would have been.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annotat.</head>
                  <p>The good people of the Nation are as much dissatisfied now as then, though through your frighting them with Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they dare not bring home to your d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ores the non-performance of former promises, why should you not thnebe, be as frequent in your meetings now as then, and never cease til you had redeemed the good old Cause, with you selv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s and the free-borne people of the Nation from this new contrived servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude under a Protector, whose intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as to perpetuate himself, and men of that Spirit, to Lord it over us, which is more destructive to the peoples liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies, than the provisson the Parliament
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115117:29"/> would have made for a new Represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative or the perpetuating themselves was like to have be.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 13. When we saw their intendment was to perpetuate themselves, and men of that spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for some had it from their own mouthes, This was a high breach of trust, if they had been a Parliament never violated, sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting as free and as clear as ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny sat in <hi>England,</hi> yet if they would go about to perpetuate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, we did think this to be so high a breach of Trust, as greater could not be, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>If it were so high a breach of trust for the Parliament, who were chosen by the people, to perpetuate themselves: Then its High Treason in your Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to do so, he being but a Ʋsurper, and forces his power upon us without our consent.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 15. But seeeing they would not give us that which might sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie us that their way was honest, and safe, they would give us leave to make our Objection; we did t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll them that we thought that way they were going in would be impracticable, we could not tell them how it would be brought to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sse, to send out an Act of Parliament into the Countrey, to have Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of an Act to be the Rules of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors, and Elected, and not to know who should execute this; desired to know whether the next
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115117:30"/> Parliament were not like to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist of all Presbyters, whether those Qual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fications would hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them or Nuters, &amp; though it be our desires to value and esteem of that judgement, onely they having as we know disserted this Cause and interest, upon the Kings accompt, and upon that closure between them and the Neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Nation, we do think we must professe, we had as good have delivered up our Cause into the hands of any, as into the hands of interested and Byast men, &amp;c. But answer was made by a very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mminent person at the same time as before, that nothing would save the Nation, but the continuance of this Parliament, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>You pretend you dissolved the Old Parliament because they made such hast with the Act for a new Rep e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative, and did not assure you the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications contained therein were so just and honest, as to keep out Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters and Neuters; and do say that to place the power so, was to threw away the Cause and the Nations Liberties, into the hands of Interested and Byast men wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> never bled for it. And that the onely way of sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ety to the Cause, was to commit the Trust to persons of Hon ur and integrity; well-affected to Religion and the interest of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115117:30"/> A second thing why they were dissolved was, because they went to perpetuate themselves: Yet notwtih<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing these fine pretences, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test part of your Protectors first Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament (so called) were Presbyters, Neuters, or worse; and the second are as bad and worse than the former. This compared with his perpetuating his power upon us, he so complained of in the Old Parliament, declares plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that he dissolved them rather to get the power into his own hand, than for the preservation of the Cause; and that he is false (as in many other things so) to this honest principle he here so much pretends to.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 16. The Government bring in that condition as it was, and things being under so ill sense abroad, and so likely to come to confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion in every respect if it went on so; we desired they would divolve the Trust over to persons of Honour and integrity, that were well known, men well-aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cted to Religion and the interest of the Nation; which we told them and was confest, was no new thing, when these Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons had been under distractions, &amp;c. We desired them to lay these things seriously to heart; They told us they would take considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them till morning; that they would sleep upon them, &amp;c. At the parting, 2. or 3. of the chiefest did tell us, they would suspend pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings with the Representative the next day, ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l they had further conference; and we did acquesse, &amp;c. The next morning we consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how to order what we had to offer to them when they were to meet in the evening, word was brought, they were proceeding with a Representative with all the eagerness they could, and had brought it to that issue, with that hast that it had never been before; leaving out the things that did necessarily relate to due qualifications, resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to make it a paper Bill, not to ingrosse it, that they might make the quicker dispatch of it; thus to have thrown all the liberties of the Nation into the hands that never bled for it: Upon this account we thought it our duty not to suffer it; and upon this the house was dissolved.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:115117:30"/>
               <p>This we tell you, that so you may know that what hath been done in dissolving this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was as necessary as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of this Cause; and that necessity that led us to do that, hath brought us to this issue of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercising an extraordinary way and course, of drawing your selves together upon this account, that you are men who know the Lord, and have made observations of his marvailous dispensations, and may be trusted with this Cause, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> having done that upon this ground of necessity which we know was not feigned, but reall and true, to the end that the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment might not be at a losse, and that we might manifest to the world the singleness of our hearts and integrity, who did those things not to grasp after the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, our selves to keep it in a Military hand, no not for a day, as far as God enable us with strength and ability to put it in the hands that might be called from seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall parts of the Nation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this necessity, this integrity of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to divest the sword of the power and Authority in the civil Administration of it hath been that, that hath moved us to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude of this course.</p>
               <p>Truly God hath called you to this work by (I think) as won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull providences, as ever past upon the Sons of men in so short a time; and truly taking the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115117:31"/> of necessity for the Government must not fall, take the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of the will of God in this thing, I am sure you would have been loath it should have been resigned into the hands of wicked men, and enemies; I am sure God would not have it so, it comes therefore to you by way of necessity; it comes to you by the way of the wise providence of God, though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hrough weak hands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you of one Scripture which hath been much upon my spirit, <hi>Hosea</hi> 11.12. <hi>Yet Judah ruleth with God, and is faithfull with the Saints,</hi> &amp;c. It is said before, <hi>Ephraim</hi> did compasse God about with lyes, and <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell</hi> with deceipt; how God hath been compassed about with fastings and thanksgivings, and other exercises, and tentations, I think we have all to lament; why truly you are called by God to be faithfull with the Saints, who have been somewhat instrumentall to your Call, <hi>He that ruleth over men</hi> (the Scripture saith) must be just, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the fear of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>You here hold forth that the many wonderfull appearances of the Lord for his people in the late Warrs, was that evill men and such as were not faithful with the Saints, and suited to the work might be laid aside, and that godly wen and men of principles, who knew the Lord and had made observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his marvailous dispensations, might be called to Rule with him, as being most lively to carry on his work, and most fit to be entrusted with his Cause; in order to this its pretended the old Parliament was dissolved and the little Parliament called, as men principled to bring forth these good things, which the former by their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stings and other exercises, did but lye to the Lord in, and did not do, and that the Government might not fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hands of wicked men and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters; as also to manifest to the world, you did not these things to grasp after the power your selves, or to keep it in a Military hand, no not for a day; this is your pretence: But doth not the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Assembly (above mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (knowingly) with contrary interests, and the turning out of them who were doing this good, and the greatest part of your Generalls Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments being Presbyters, Neuters, and worse (not near so good as the old Parliament he so complains of) hold clearly, that all these pretended ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities (as to him) were of his own making, and but as so many blindes to cover his designe of exalting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 21. I think I need as little advise you about propogation of the Gospell, and encourageing such Ministers and such a Ministry as be faithfull in the Land, upon whom the true Character is, men that have truly received the spirit for such a use, as Christians will be well able to discern and do, <hi>&amp;c. Page</hi> 22. I speak not it is far from my heart, for a Ministry deriving it selfe thorough the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sie, and and pretending to that which is so much insisted upon to be successi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the true succession is through the Spirit, given in that measure as the Spirit is given, and that is a right succession, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I confesse I never lookt to see such a day as this, it may be nor
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115117:31"/> you, when Jesus Christ shall be owned as he is this day: Jesus Christ is owned this day by you all, by your willingness in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing here, and you manifest this as farre as poor creatures can, to be a day of the power of Christ, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having through so much blood and tryalls as have been upon these Nations, made this to be one of the great issues thereof, to have a people called to the Supream Authority upon an avowed accompt God hath owned his Sonne by this; and you by your willingnesse do own Jesus Christ; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for my part, I confesse I did never look to see such a light; we have not allowed our selves in the choice of one person in whom we had not this good hope, that there was faith in Jesus Christ and love unto all the Saints: And thus God hath owned you, and by your coming together have you owned him, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>You are as like the forming of God as ever a people were, if any man should ask you, and tender a Book to you, you will dare to swear that neither directly, nor indirectly did you seek to come hither, you have been p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssive in coming hither, &amp;c. Consider the Circumstances by which you are Called, through what Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; through what st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ivings; through what bloud you are come, hither, &amp;c. I say nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple form'd for such a purpose (so Called) if it were time to compare your standing with those that have been called by the suffer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ges of the people, who can tell you how soon God can fit the people for such a thing; and who would
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115117:32"/> desire any thing more in the world, but that it might be so? I would that all the Lords people were Prophets! I would they were fit to be called, or fit to call! And it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the longing of our hearts to see them once own the Interest of Jesus Christ. What a duty will lye upon you to have your Conversation such, as that they may love you; that they may see you lay out your time and spirit for them: Is not this the most likely way to bring them to their liberties? And do you not by this put i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> up n God to stode the time and the season for it, by pouring forth his spirit, at least by convincing them that as men fearing God, have fought them out of their thraldome and bondage under the legall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; so men fearing God, rule them in the fear of God, and take care to administer good things unto them? &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot.</head>
                  <p>You here pretend to have a great care of those who receive their Ministry from the spirit, and that its far from your heart to speak for the Nationall Clergy, who deriving their standing through the Papacy, you say is a false Succession: But now the tide is so turned, that the encouragement, or disencouragement is upon the owning, or not owning your Generalls Ʋsurpt power; for though men be never so spirituall and able to teach, and th s known before hand, yet if out of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce they cannot how to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yers (that Image of the Beast▪) then that encouragement they formerly had upon this accompt is taken away, though they and their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies perish; whilest the others submitting to them are encouraged, to hale the people of God and others to prisons for not putting into their mouths; and yet you are so impudent as to tell us, you are not at all changed from what you were when you spake these words.</p>
                  <p>By these words you declare you were forgetting things behind and pressing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115117:31"/> towards the Kingdome of Christ, and to act as upon his foundation, so in his Name; and therefore judged it your duty to choose none but Believers, who had love to all the Saints as being most suitable to that Kingdome. But com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring these words with present acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, there is just ground to say, that you who did thus pretend to begin in the spirit, are ending in the flesh; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning that good way you here seem to approve of.</p>
                  <p>And if their being Saints and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly nor indirectly seeking to come into power but were c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lled by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers was, such a manifestation they were formed of God: Then who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them, who sued to this party and the other, wooing and disiring them to make parties for them, and using other indirect means; as giving money to some, and paying the Boat hire and charges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of others, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ending in whole Beeves, Mutt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Venison Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties, Wine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to encourage the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to chuse them; and this done in a wicked disorderly manner, to the great dishonour of God, the grief of his people and the further prejudice of his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Cause; surely it is very unlikely that such persons as these should own the Interest of Jesus Christ, or bring the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115117:32"/> people to their liberties, but rather to be slaves and vassals to your Protectors Interest, which unworthy carriage of his, in suffering things to go in this way after such glorious words for Jesus Christ, can be tearmd no other but wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full back sliding, which the Lord with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eminent repentance will charge home upon him.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:115117:30"/>
               <p>I say you are called with a high call, and why should we be afrayd to say or think that this may be the doore to usher in things, that God hath promised, and prophesi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d of, and to set the hearts of his people to wait for and expect; we know who they are that shall warr with the Lamb, aginst his enemies, they shall be a people called, chosen &amp; faithfull, and hath in the Millita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y way, I believe you know it, he hath acted with them, and for them, and now in the civill power and Authority, &amp; these are not ill prognostications of that good we wait for &amp; expect, I do think some thing is at the doore, we are at the threshold, and therefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes us to lift up our heads, and to encourage our selves in the Lord, and we have some of us thought it our du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, not vainly looking at the prophesie in <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. <hi>And the Kingdome shall not be delivered to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people.</hi> Truly God hath brought it into your hands by his own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssing, and calling out a Millitary power, God hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded their hearts to be instrumentall in calling you, and this hath been set upon our hearts, and upon all the faithfull in the land, it may be it is not our duty to deliver it over to any other people, and that Scripture may be fulfilling now to us; but I may go beyond my time.</p>
               <p>But I thanke God I have my hopes exercised in these things, and so I am perswaded are yours; truly seeing things are so that you are at the edge of the promises, &amp; prophesies, at least if there were n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ither promise for this nor prophesy, your coveting the best things, endeavouring after the best things, and as I have said elsewhear if I wear to chuse the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:115117:32"/> Officer in the Army, or Common-wealth, I would chuse a godly man that hath principles, especially where trust is to be committed, for I know where to have a man of principles: I believe if any of you should chuse a servant you would do so, and I would all our Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates were so chosen, that may be some effects of this, it is our duty to chuse men that fear the Lord, to praise the Lord, yea such as the Lord formes for himselfe, and he expects not prayses from others. This being so, it puts me in minde of an other Scripture, <hi>Mal.</hi> 6.8. which indeed is a glorious prophesy, and I am perswaded of the Gospell, or it may be of the Jews, also there it is prophesied he will bring his people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain out of the depths of the Sea, as once he led Israell through the red Sea, and it may be some doe think God is bringing the Jewes home to their station from the Isles of the Sea. Surely when God sets up his Gospell-Church, it shall be gathering people out of deep waters, out of the multitude of waters, such are his people drawn out of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Nations and people of the world, and that <hi>Psalm</hi> will be very glorious in many other parts of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When he gave the Word great was the company of them that publisht it, Kings of the Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es did fly a pace, and shee that tarryed at home devided the spoyle, and although ye have layen among the potts, yet shall ye be as the wings of a dove covered with silver, and her feathers with yellow gold.</hi> And indeed the triumph of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at Psalm is exceeding high and great, and God is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishing it, and the close of it, that closeth with my heart, and I am perswaded will with yours also. <hi>That God makes Hills and Mountains and they reel,</hi> and God hath a Hill too, <hi>and his Hill is as the Hill of</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shan, <hi>and the Charriots of God are</hi> 20000. <hi>of Angells, and God will dwell u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this hill for ever.</hi> All that I have to say in my own, and in the name of my fellow Officers (who have joyned with me in this worke) that we shall commend you to the grace of God, and to the guidance of his Spirit, having thus farre served you or rather our Lord Jesus Christ in it; we are as we hope and shall be ready in our stations, according as the providenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of God shall lead us, to be subservient to the work of God and the Authority which we reckon God hath set over us. And although we have no formall thing to present you with, to which the hands and outward visible expressions of the hearts of the Officers of the three Nations are set, yet we may say for them, and we may say also with confidence that our Brethren at Sea, with whom neither in <hi>Scotland,</hi> nor <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor at Sea hath any ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifice been used, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade their approb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions to this work; yet we can say that their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent and affections hath flowed in to us b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yond our expectations, and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115117:33"/> we may say with all confidence that we have had their approbation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and full consent unsought indeed to the other work; so that you have their hearts and affections in this; and not onely they, but we have very many Papers from the Churches of God throughout the Nation, wonderfully both approving what hath been done in removing obsta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and approving what hath been done in this very thing.</p>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>Annot</head>
                  <p>In the latter part of this Speech you may take notice what g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orious wordes you have spoken for the kingdome of Christ, and that glory which is to be revealed in the latter dayes, and what encouragement you give the Saints to believe that the little Stone had been at worke already, or was nigh its comming for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h as in that quoted place, <hi>Dan. 2.44.</hi> And that something was at the Door<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, that we w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re at the very edge and Threshold of the Prophesie and Promises being fulfill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that God was bringing home the Jews to their station from the Isl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Sea, and what shakings of Mountains and Hills there will be, when this work comes forth; and do exhort us to lift up our heads in the expectation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to encou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>age our s lv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s in the Lord: And though there were neither promise nor prophesy to be fulfilled, yet it was our duty, to covet, and endeavour after the best things, and to be as refined and spirituall as is possible in the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the world, as well as of particular persons, or families, it being a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uty to chuse men who fear the Lord to praise the Lord, such as he formes for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and he expects not praises f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om others: and you pretend to put th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples into practice in calling the Little Parliament together; in chusing of whom what ever your intentions were, yet surely those who were faithfull of them, sat there in answer to the faith &amp; prayers of those Sts. who had not defil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but desired with more refinedness to act up to their former Ʋirgin princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, &amp; those promises, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then made to the Lord &amp; his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ople in the daies of our streghits: And also had the approbation of those mentiond in the end of the speech without any artifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> used to pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>swade them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hereto; &amp; whilest they sat th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re was a generall rejoycing among all go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d men whose hearts went along w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h the work of God in that da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; and th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Off e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s and Souldiers durst speak their minds freel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and encourage one anoth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r in these honost principles, and to oppose Tyranny and wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dnesse where ever they saw it, and we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e growing up a mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in these glorious things, and attained to such a blessed frame of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i it, as to be willing to follow the Lord into <hi>F ance, Spain, Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>▪</hi> or where ever he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d any work for them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o: And as it was a day of joy to the good people, so it was of terrour and sadnesse to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e loose Clergy, Lawyers and the wicked of our own and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions abroad, every one wonde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing and looking what would be the end of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sence we had then among us. But since your Generall and you with him, declined from these honest principles, and turned those honest men before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115117:33"/> out of the Listle Parleament, who were going on in the worke, according to these honest principles; and usurpt the power into his own hand he had so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared against, and sat down upon the seat of the Beast, and fell a persecuting some and imprisoning other of the Saints, and to blaspheme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Lords Spirit, in saying, they were acted by the Spirit of the Devill, for no other cause the Lord knowes, but their faithfulnesse to him in pressing after these very things you here so much declare for, and opposing your back sliding, and building what had been destroyed: Now since you came to do these wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ked things, this glorious presence which was then with you is departed, as appears in his, as eminently blasting your designes now, as ever he bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t you before, witnesse your great defeat and disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyntment at <hi>Hyspaniola,</hi> the losse of some thousands of men at <hi>Jamica,</hi> the in succesfulnesse of the Fleet in the <hi>Straights</hi> these two years together, the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of the enemy heightened, the great losses and cowardlinesse of your men in the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rrow Seas, the corrupt Interests before mentioned lifting up their heads, and rejoycing the Nations abroad, contemning and scorning us. The lively Spirit which was once in the Army now choakt and lost, the hearts of the Saints which were formerly with you, now grieved and engaged against you; and to add to this the blessed Cause and wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke of Christ is stopped and hindered: All which considered it is high time you awake out of this back-sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ding state, and break off your sins by r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pentance, and walking with more refinednesse than ever, according to your good old p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inciples, and thereby redeem the almost three years time you have now lost, that so the Lords former presence may again be with you if he shall please to use you any further in his worke; in ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r to which, repair to you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all, and endeavour all you can to convince him of his evill (if that be yet to do) and when you have done so (after humbling himselfe before the Lord and his people) to go to that very place at <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>stminster</hi> where he tooke up his new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived dignity (that child of his sorrow) and to throw down and trample upon his Chayr of State, and all that pomp and bravery prepared for that s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mnity; and to declare before the Lord, his people, and the Nation, his sorrow and unfeigned repentance, as for other things, so for persecuting his Brethren, whom he made once believe was as dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to him as his own Soul, and for no other cause then is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mentioned: As olso for his taking upon him that accursed thing (the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchicall Government with its oppurtenances) which himsel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thers had declared and witnessed against, with so vast an expence of blood and treasure, and had been so in trumental to destroy: If ever it be well with you, there must be some kind or other of manifest reall repentance, because the dishonour which hath been brought upon the Name and wayes of God h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th been so publique, and there is nothing less can help him, for the wound he hath received from the Lord in endeavouring to heal the deadly wound of the Beast is so great, that all the renewed change of his Parliament, or Presbyterian plaister, nor any other daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115117:34"/> means he shall use can heal it, for the Lord hath so appointed that onely they who confesse, and forsake their sins shall have mercy: The which if the Lord of his grace shall please to work in him and you, would exceedingly rejoyce their hearts, who have good reason to cease from man; and in all their speaking and actings in this day dersie to be found purely and alone for the advancement of the Blessed Cause and Interest of our Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS,</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POST SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THe designe of this Collection out of the Choicest and most Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of the Armies Declarations, Remonstrances, &amp;c. among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, is chiefly to bring to your Remembrance that Excellent Frame which formerly and of late appeared to be upon the hearts of the then honest Officers and Souldiers of the English Armies till their late Declention. From the beginning of the Book till you come to the Declaration of <hi>August</hi> 1. 1650. Dated at <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stbrough</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> you may see what a blessed Spirit you se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>med to be acted by for the peoples Liberties against Monarchy a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Tyranny. The three Acts and the Engagement of Parliament are added, because they are suitable to what goes before, and of your own procuring. From the fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Declaration to the end of the Book you do carry it higher, and do seem to presse towards the advancement of the Kingdome of Jesus Christ, at least th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t you shoud be coveting and endeavouring after the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st things. The Annotations running along by them, are in some measure to declare how, and wherein you are Declined from those honest Principles to Monarchy, Tyranny, and loosnesse, which indeed is so plain that he who runs may read it. And although most of you do acknowledge you are out of the way, and that things are not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they ought to be; yet you sit still enjoying your pay, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour all you can to muzle your Consciences, and to excuse your selves therein by saying, a Souldier is a lawfull employment; and that good men were Souldiers formerly under wicked Rulers; as if their standing and yours were all one; take heed how you wind and turn the Scriptures like a Nose of Wax to serve your lusts, for when you have done all you can it will not help you: For as that Dispensation they then were under and the present which is upon us doth differ (as your selves also Confesse in Declaration from <hi>Mustbrough</hi> before-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115117:34"/> where you say; the Lord was come to put on the Saints beautifull garments and to make them a praise in the Earth; to destroy the Whore and to burn her fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sh with fire) So their being Souldiers was by a common providence, or by accident, or probably as one man is of this Calling, and another of that to get a livelihood. But were never raised up and called forth by the Lord from their private Callings, and encouraged by a Parliaments Declarations, to engage for the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the peoples Liberties in opposition to Tyranny and Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; to dest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y Antichrist, and for the advancement of the Kingdom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Jesus Christ, as you have been, and have declared you engaged not herein as a Mercinary Army hired to serve the Arbitrary power of a State, nor as Souldiers of Fortune and servants of men; but out of Judgement and Conscience, upon the accompt and for the ends a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid as appears in Declaration 14. <hi>June,</hi> 1647. and the Declaration in <hi>Scotland</hi> before quoted, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you look into the Case of the Army Stated Page 4. and in the 17. Page of this Book you may see you could argue thus against <hi>Hollis</hi> and <hi>Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leton</hi> and that Faction, who were for the Kings Interest in that day; who you so opposed for no othe cause than that they would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ve given t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e King that Power and Trust your Protector hath now assum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to himself. If this be so, then surely you cannot honestly in the least p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d your standing to be lawfull and good form theirs, nor upon any o h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccompt whatsoever, so long as this backsliding con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. Th p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>cuted Cause of Christ, and his Spirit in his S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their faithfulln<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sse thereto, and to these honest Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ciple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>s for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>timony, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is t e duty of all those who have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> things; to forsak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Father, Mother Wife, &amp;c. Estate, yea life it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and therein to follow the Lord ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whethersoever he goes; for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s are to overcome the Beast and false Prophet, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll who are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted by that Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it <hi>by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bloud of the Lamb, the word of their Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>timony and they lived not their lives unto the death,</hi> Rev. 12.11. Therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s your duty while you keep up Armes, to endeavour to see those t ings brought forth for whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h you took them up at first, and if you cannot by perswasion on the ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> h nd, or are not free to oppose your Protecto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on the other, as you did th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King upon the same accompt; then you are by laying down and disserting th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, to declare you approve not of their actions, and can have no fellowship with them in these unfruitfull works of darknesse: But if notwithstanding upon worldly c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nsiderations you will yet k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>p up; then know you ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not called by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ples Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentors for the preservation of their Rights and Freedomes; and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:115117:35"/> for the advancement of the Kingdome of Christ as you were before, but are meer Mercinaries, and upholders of the same and greater Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny in your Protector, which hath cost so much Bloud and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to oppose in the King. And if any shall yet Object and say, your way is good and we are mistaken; The answer i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, if your way were of God and according to his good will and pleasure, it would be more pure and spirituall, and for the glory of God than the Govrnment which was before it, and more agreeing with what it shall be, when the Prophesies and Promises are fulfilled, <hi>Isa.</hi> 32.1, 2. <hi>Micha</hi> 4.1, 2. <hi>Psal.</hi> 72. And to that honest spirit in the fore-going Speech you seem to be acted by: But its clearly evident you are not so, but are gone back with your Captain to those old Aegyptian practices, which you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Lord by his wonderfull dispensations had brought you from: So that no man who approves his heart to the Lord, and is not a flattering time-server for his own advantage, can truly say you are so honest as to endeavour after the best things you so pretended to, but are gone back to Aegypt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list">
            <head>Here followes a Catalogue of the severall Declarations Remonst<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> out of which this Collction is taken.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> Declaration <hi>June 14. 1647.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> A Representation</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> A Letter to the Generall concerning the large Petition delivered to the Parliament <hi>Sept. 11, 1648.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> large Petition</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> A Gratulatory Letter from divers Officers to the Presentors of that Petition</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> Case of the Army Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> Remonstrance from <hi>Albons</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> Abridgment of that Remonstrance</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> Petiton annexed to the Agreement of the people</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> The Agreement of the people</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> A Declaration annex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to it</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12</hi> A Letter from five Regiments of horse encouraging the people to it</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13</hi> Three Acts of Parliament and the Engagement against Monarchy</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> A Declaration of the Army <hi>19 Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 1650</hi> going to <hi>Scotland</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15</hi> A Declaration in <hi>Scotland Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 1650.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17</hi> A Declaration after the old Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament was Dissolved</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18</hi> Gen. <hi>Cromwells</hi> Speech to the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Parliament before their sitting</item>
            </list>
            <p>Protector and Generall is all one, onely Protector is sometimes put for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction sake.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115117:35"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>